<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peoples right to read the Holy Scripture asserted in answer to the 6th, 7th, 8th, 9th, and 10th chapters, of the second part of the Popish representer.</title>
            <author>Stratford, Nicholas, 1633-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9008</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11806579</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11806579</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 550:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peoples right to read the Holy Scripture asserted in answer to the 6th, 7th, 8th, 9th, and 10th chapters, of the second part of the Popish representer.</title>
                  <author>Stratford, Nicholas, 1633-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Appears as v. 5 of the 1848 ed.: A preservative against popery / edited by Edmund Gibson.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Nicholas Stratford. cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Study and teaching.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Study and teaching --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Use.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49460:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Peoples Right To Read the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> ASSERTED. In ANSWER to the <hi>6th, 7th, 8th, 9th,</hi> and <hi>10th</hi> Chapters, of the Second Part of the POPISH REPRESENTER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49460:2"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>IMPRIMATUR,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen. Maurice,</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> in Chriſto P. D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Archiepiſcop. Cant. a Sacris.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Maii 27. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49460:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49460:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49460:3"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <head>Four Things propoſed to be treated of.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I.</hi> WHAT the Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this this Matter is.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>II.</hi> That this Practice is plainly contrary to the Will of God, to the Reaſon of the Thing, and to the Practice of the Chriſtian Church, for more than a thouſand Years after Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The Inſufficiency of thoſe Reaſons, by which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> endeavours to juſtify it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> The Truth of thoſe Inferences the Proteſtants draw from it. <hi>Page</hi> 1, 2.</item>
               </list> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label>
                  <item>THE Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this Matter repreſented, <hi>Pag.</hi> 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label>
                  <item>THE Contrariety of this Practice to the Will of God, to Reaſon, and to the Practice of the Chriſtian Church for more than a thouſand Years, <hi>Pag.</hi> 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. I.</hi> It's contrariety to the Will of God, appears, in that God,
<list>
                              <item>1. Cauſed the Scriptures to be written in a Language underſtood by the Vulgar, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9.</item>
                              <item>2. Adreſs'd them to the Vulgar, <hi>Pag.</hi> 11.</item>
                              <item>3. Commanded the Vulgar to converſe familiarly with them, <hi>Pag.</hi> 12.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. II.</hi> It's contrariety to Reaſon ſhew'd both from the Scope and End of the Scriptures, and from the Teſtimonies of many Learned Men of the Church of <hi>Rome, Pag.</hi> 14</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. III.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>It's contrariety to the Practice of the Chriſtian Church, proved by unqueſtionable Teſtimonies, for twelve hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years downward, <hi>p.</hi> 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>When and upon what occaſion, a Reſtraint was firſt laid upon the reading of the Scriptures, <hi>p.</hi> 26</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label>
                  <item>THE Reaſons the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> offers to juſtify this Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome, Pag.</hi> 27
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. I.</hi> The general Reaſon <hi>(viz.</hi> the Miſchiefs that ariſe from the promiſcuous reading of the Scripture) <hi>conſider'd, and the abſurdity of it expoſed, p.</hi> 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. II.</hi> The Miſchiefs objected are all of the ſame kind. <hi>p.</hi> 33In particular theſe three;
<list>
                              <item>1. The Diviſions that are among Chriſtians.</item>
                              <item>2. As many different Bibles as there are different Heads.</item>
                              <item>3. Not only ſeveral Perſons, but the ſame Perſon many times hath different Bibles.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>I.</hi> That the Diviſions among Chriſtians ariſe ſolely or principally from the reading of the Bible by the Vulgar. 1. It is notoriouſly falſe. 2. In caſe it were true, it would not be of force to infer his Concluſion. <hi>p.</hi> 36 It is notoriouſly falſe. In that,
<list>
                                    <item>1. There were Diviſions among the ancient Guides of the Church. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>2. There have been, and ſtill are, Diviſions, yea, as many among the <hi>Learned</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as among the <hi>Proteſtants. p.</hi> 37</item>
                                    <item>The Learned Romaniſts are divided among themſelves, in all thoſe Points in which they are divided from <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. ibid.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <pb facs="tcp:49460:4"/>
                                    <item>4. Thoſe very pernicious Doctrines and Practices, which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> himſelf mentions, are deriv'd from the Learned; eſpecially from the Learned of the Church of <hi>Rome. p.</hi> 39</item>
                                    <item>5. The Diviſions among the Vulgar, for the moſt part are not owing to themſelves, but to the Learned. 41</item>
                                 </list> If it were true, that the Diviſions among Chriſtians ariſe from the reading of the Bible by the Vulgar; yet it would not be ſufficient Reaſon for denying the Bible to them. <hi>p.</hi> 42</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>II.</hi> The ſecond Miſchief, <hi>viz.</hi> If the Bible be allowed the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, there will be as many different Bibles among them as there are Heads. <hi>p.</hi> 43 That every difference in Senſe, makes not a different Bible, <hi>p.</hi> 44 The vanity of this Reaſon appears, in that,
<list>
                                    <item>1. It is of equal force againſt the reading of the Scripture by the Learned, yea of much greater. <hi>p.</hi> 45</item>
                                    <item>2. Where the Vulgar are not permitted to read the Bible, there are as many different Bibles (in the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Senſe) as where they are, <hi>p.</hi> 46</item>
                                    <item>3. The Argument retorted. <hi>p.</hi> 47</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>III.</hi> The third Miſchief may alſo be objected with as much Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, againſt the reading of the Scripture by the Learned; particularly, by the Roman Biſhops, Cardinals and Popes. <hi>p.</hi> 48</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. III.</hi> The Reaſons the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> gives, why the Vulgar ſo differ in the ſenſe of Scripture, are two, <hi>viz.</hi> The Obſcurity of the Scripture, and the ſetting up every Man's private Reaſon to be judg of it. <hi>p.</hi> 50
<list>
                              <item>1. The Obſcurity of the Scriptures. <hi>ibid.</hi> What the Proteſtants affirm of the plainneſs of the Scripture, is no more than what the Ancient Fathers, what the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> formerly, and what many Learned <hi>Romaniſts</hi> of this preſent Age have affirm'd. <hi>p.</hi> 51 That the Diſagreement about the ſenſe of Scripture, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from the obſcurity of it. <hi>p.</hi> 52 From whence this Diſagreement proceeds. <hi>p.</hi> 53</item>
                              <item>2. The ſetting up every Man's private Reaſon to be judg of Scripture, <hi>p.</hi> 54 The Proteſtants make not Reaſon judg of Scripture, as the Socinians do, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:49460:5"/>They make Reaſon no otherwiſe Judg, than as our Bleſſed Saviour and his Apoſtles have allowed &amp; commanded. <hi>p.</hi> 55 The Clergy of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> notwithſtanding their loud Cry againſt private Reaſon, make it Judg as much as Proteſtants. <hi>p.</hi> 56 His Argument from the <hi>Oneneſs</hi> of the Chriſtian Faith, anſwered and retorted. <hi>p.</hi> 57, 58, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His other Arguments from the Authority of the Church, the Creed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 17. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. <hi>p.</hi> 61, 62, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
                  <item>THE falſe Conſtructions, or wrong Inferences (as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> calls them) which the Proteſtants make from this Practice, are three;
<list>
                        <item>1. That the Vulgar Papiſts are deprived of the Word of God.</item>
                        <item>2. That they take up all their Belief upon truſt.</item>
                        <item>3. That the Reaſon why they are not permitted to read the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is for fear leaſt they ſhould diſcover the Errors of their Religion. <hi>p.</hi> 65<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. I.</hi> The firſt Proteſtant Inference juſtified; and the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi>'s Reaſons to the contrary, ſhew'd to be idle and inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. <hi>p.</hi> 65, 66, 67, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. II.</hi> That the Vulgar Papiſt takes all his Belief upon truſt. <hi>p.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> This ſhew'd in each of thoſe Heads mentioned by the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenter.</hi> And the abſurdity of his Reaſons to the contrary ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> manifeſt. <hi>p.</hi> 71, 72, 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>SECT. III.</hi> The third Inference vindicated, and his two Reaſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> it ſhew'd to be of no force. <hi>p.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> No thanks to them that the Bible is not denied the Learned. <hi>p.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> That it is the Bible it ſelf they look upon as miſchievous. <hi>p.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Some Learned Men not ſo well qualified to diſcover their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rors as ſome of the Vulgar. <hi>p.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Many of their Learned Men have diſcovered their Errors. <hi>p.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Why more liberty is given to their Vulgar here in <hi>Engla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> than in other Countries. <hi>p.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> That the Vulgar here in <hi>England</hi> have diſcovered their Err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49460:5"/>
            <head>The Peoples Right to read the Holy Scripture aſſerted.</head>
            <p>THough <hi>it is as evident, as that the Scripture is in Print,</hi> that the free Uſe of it, is by the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy denied to the <hi>Vulgar;</hi> yet when they are charged with it by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> they either take the confidence plainly to deny it; or if they own the Charge (as the Repreſenter doth) they endeavour to put ſuch gloſſes upon it, as to make their <hi>denial</hi> of the Scripture, to be in effect, but a better way of <hi>granting</hi> it: For ſince it is not the <hi>words</hi> of the Bible, but the <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> of the words, that is properly the <hi>Word of God;</hi> while they withhold from them the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> they provide means to acquaint them with the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> or the <hi>true ſenſe</hi> of Scripture; and ſo deliver it to them with much more advantage, than People of any <hi>other Perſwaſion</hi> have it.</p>
            <p>What others have formerly written for their Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in this Matter, it is needleſs now to examine; ſince it is not to be ſuppoſed, but that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> hath ſaid as much to the purpoſe, as any of thoſe who have gone before him. I ſhall therefore confine the enſuing Diſcourſe, to what he hath ſaid in his <hi>6th, 7th, 8th, 9th,</hi> and <hi>10th</hi> Chapters. And that it may be the more clear and ſatisfactory, I ſhall ſhew theſe four Things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49460:6"/> I. <hi>What is the Practice of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>in this Matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>That this Practice is plainly contrary to the Will of</hi> God, <hi>to the Reaſon of the Thing, and to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Chriſtian Church, for more than a thouſand Years after Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>The inſufficiency of thoſe Reaſons, by which the</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter <hi>endeavours to juſtify it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Vindicate thoſe Inferences the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>draw from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that is ſaid by the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> may, I think, be reduced to one or other of theſe Heads.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THough ſome may think it needleſs to inſiſt upon the firſt of theſe, ſince what the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with in this Matter, is freely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough owned by the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> himſelf <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 45, 46. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 52. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 57.</note>; yet becauſe ſome of that Communion here in <hi>England,</hi> (who for <hi>prudential</hi> Reaſons, are not ſo ſtraitly tied up) do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently deny it; it may not be amiſs, for their infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to give ſome ſhort account of it, from better Authority than that of the <hi>Repreſenter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which we need go no further than the fourth Rule of the <hi>Trent</hi> Expurgatory Index, which is this: <hi>Since it is manifeſt by experience, that if the Holy Bible be promiſcuouſly permitted in the vulgar Tongue, by reaſon of the raſhneſs of Men, more Loſs than Profit will thence ariſe: In this Matter, let the Judgment of the Biſhop or</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49460:6"/> 
                  <hi>Inquiſitor be ſtood to, that with the advice of the Pariſh Prieſt or Confeſſor, they may grant the reading of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the vulgar Tongue, tranſlated by Catholick Authors, to ſuch as they ſhall underſtand can receive no hurt by ſuch reading, but increaſe of Faith and Piety. Which Faculty let them have in writing. But he, that without ſuch Faculty, ſhall preſume to read, or to have the Bible, he may not receive Abſolution of his Sins, except he firſt deliver up his Bible to the Ordinary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any Man ſhall ſay, That this Rule hath not the force of a Law, <hi>Monſieur de Maire,</hi> Counſellor, Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Preacher to the King of <hi>France,</hi> in a Book pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Authority, ſhall give him an Anſwer: <hi>This Rule,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is founded in Eccleſiaſtical Right, and no Man can tranſgreſs it, without contradicting that Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which he owes to the Church, and the Holy See, from which it hath received its Confirmation: Foraſmuch as this Rule was not made but in proſecution of the Decree of the Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>&amp;c. no Man can deny, but that it hath been approved by the Holy Sea, and authorized by the Bulls of</hi> Pius <hi>IV, and</hi> Clement <hi>VIII; who after they had view'd and diligently examin'd it, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd it to the World, with Order that it ſhould be obey'd.</hi> 
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Enfin je maintiens que cette Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle eſt fondeé en droict Eccleſiaſtique, et qu' on ne la peut violer ſans cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer l'obeïſſance qu' l'on doit à l'Egliſe, &amp;c. Le Sanctuaire ſerme aux Profanes, part. 3. c. 1. p. 335, 336.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If,</hi> ſays he, <hi>there be any thing that can hinder this Rule from having the Force of a Law, it muſt be either becauſe it hath not been publiſhed, or being publiſhed, hath not been received: but neither the one nor the other can be ſaid, ſince it is evident, that this is the old Quarrel we have with our Hereticks; that this is that which our Church hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been upbraided with by the Enemies of the Faith; this is that which is the Subject of their moſt outragious Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies; this is that which hath been acknowledged by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49460:7"/> 
                  <hi>wiſe Men; that which hath been earneſtly maintained by all the Defenders of Catholick Truths,</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">—Ce que perſonne n' igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; ce que tout le monde publie, n' y aiant point de creance plus commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ny plus generale parmy les fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, &amp;c. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that which no Perſon is ignorant of; that which the whole World pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes; there being no Point of Belief more common, nor more general among the Faithful, than this of the Prohibition to read the Bible without permiſſion. And this Belief ſo common, is</hi> (ſays he) <hi>a certain Proof, not only of the publication, but of the reception of this Rule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It cannot be denied, but that it hath been received by all thoſe Nations, by which the Decrees of <hi>Trent</hi> were univerſally received: And ſo they were, as <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lavicino</hi> tells us <note n="d" place="margin">Pallav. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>c.</hi> 9, 11, 12, 13.</note> in <hi>Italy, Spain, Sicily, Portugal, Poland,</hi> the greater part of <hi>Germany,</hi> and many other Countries.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe this Rule were not received as impoſed by the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> yet in all Popiſh Countries they have made it a Law to themſelves. It is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed obſerved in <hi>France,</hi> upon the Authority of the Council; but they have ſet it up, and eſtabliſhed it as a Law by their own Authority, as is manifeſt by the Mandates of their Archbiſhops and Biſhops, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of their Provincial Councils, and the Edicts and Arreſts of their Kings and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <note n="e" place="margin">La Bible Deffendue au Vulgai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Part. 3. c. 1, &amp; 4. Collectio Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. Verſiones Vulg. damnant.</note>. It is true, there is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more latitude in <hi>France</hi> for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Licence, for not only the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and his Vicar-General, but the Penitentiary, or a Man's own Pariſh Prieſt may grant it <note n="f" place="margin">Mandeuent de Monſeigneur L' Archeveſque de Paris portant defenſe de lire la Bible en Langue Vulgaire ſans permiſſion. Fait le 2 Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, 1650.</note>. But then to make an amends for this, in other Countries, the Rule is made ſtricter than it was at firſt by the <hi>Trent</hi> Fathers; for that does
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49460:7"/> not forbid the Vulgar Bible, but only the reading it without a Licence; whereas the <hi>5th</hi> Rule of the <hi>Spaniſh Index,</hi> prohibits the Bibles themſelves in the Vulgar Tongue, and all Parts of them too; and that not only Printed, but in Manuſcript.
<note n="g" place="margin">Prohibentur Biblia lingua vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari extantia, cum omnibus earum partibus impreſſis aut Manuſcriptis; pariter ſummaria &amp; compendia quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis hiſtorica, eorundam Bibliorum, aut librorum ſacrae Scripturae, idio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate aut lingua vulgari.</note> And <hi>Alfonſus de Caſtro</hi> tells us, <hi>That</hi> Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand <hi>King of</hi> Spain <hi>forbad any Man under the heavieſt Penalties, to tranſlate the Bible into the Vulgar Tongue, or to keep any Bible in his Hands already tranſlated.</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Alfonſ. de Caſtro adverſ. Haereſ. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> And in the <hi>Index</hi> of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VII, not only thoſe Bibles that are tranſlated and printed by Hereticks; but all Bibles in any Vulgar Tongue are prohibited <note n="i" place="margin">Biblia vulgari quocunque idio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate conſcripta.</note>. Yea ſo careful are the Clergy in moſt Popiſh Countries to keep the Laity from the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Scriptures, that, as Sir <hi>Edwin Sandys</hi> relates, in their very Sermons, tho they preach for the moſt part on the Goſpel of the Day, yet they do not read, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe recite the Text, but diſcourſe only on ſuch Points of it, as they think fitteſt, that no ſound of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may poſſeſs the People. I ſay, <hi>in moſt Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> becauſe the uſe of <hi>France,</hi> as he ſays, is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. <note n="k" place="margin">Sandys's Europae Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. <hi>p.</hi> 126, 127.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It would be therefore ridiculous, in <hi>Spain,</hi> to talk of a Licence, becauſe the Bible it ſelf is not there permitted in the Vulgar Tongue. And all that is permitted in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries, where the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> bears ſway without controul, is, that a Man may read the Holy Scripture, in caſe he can get a Licence for it.</p>
               <p>But now, to whom may this Licence be granted? What, to all Men indifferently, who ask it? No; but to thoſe only <hi>who they know can receive no hurt, but encreaſe</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49460:8"/> 
                  <hi>of Faith and Piety thereby</hi> 
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">—Quos intellexerint ex hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi lectione, non damnum, ſed fidei atque Pietatis augmentum capere poſſe.</note>. That is, as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>Thoſe who are not in danger of preferring their own Senſe, before that which they receive from their Paſtors, and the Church</hi> 
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">Chap. 7. p. 52.</note>. And may it not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, that theſe Men will never ſo much as ask it? For to what purpoſe ſhould they deſire to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who are already reſolved (right or wrong) to believe as the Prieſt bids them? Yea, ſo far are they from deſiring it, that they reckon it a Mortal Sin. And ſhould others preſume to ask it, it would be denied them; becauſe they cannot ſo much as ask it, but they will be ſuſpected to be of the number of thoſe Perſons, who are in the greateſt danger of receiving hurt by it. So that upon the whole Matter, the great noiſe they make of Licences, is but a meer Sham; ſince thoſe of the Vulgar who might perhaps obtain them, are never likely to ask them; and thoſe who will be moſt forward to ask them, will never be able to obtain them.</p>
               <p>And that it was indeed a Device of the Clergy, to get the Bible again out of the Hands of the People, among whom it was then diſperſed, is plain enough; becauſe whoſoever had got a Bible, and had not a Licence, he might not receive Abſolution of his Sins, unleſs he firſt delivered up his Bible to the Ordinary. And having thus got the Bible again into their own keeping, that they deſigned, as much as poſſible, to keep it for the future out of the Hands of the People, is further manifeſt, from the addition made to this Rule, by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> VIII, upon the new Impreſſion of it, viz. <hi>That by this Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Edition no new Faculty is given to Biſhops or Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors, or any Superiors of Regulars, to grant a Licence of buying, reading, or retaining the Bible in the Vulgar Tongue;</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49460:8"/> 
                  <hi>ſince hitherto by the command and uſage of the Holy, Roman and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Inquiſition, that Faculty of granting ſuch Licences, of reading or retaining the Vulgar Bibles, or any parts of the Holy Scriptures, as well of the New as the Old Teſtament, in any Vulgar Tongue, hath been taken from them. Which,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is to be inviolably obſerved</hi> 
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">Obſervat. Clement. VIII. circa Reg. quartam Trid.</note>. If then this Power formerly given of granting Licences be taken away, and no new Power of granting them gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it neceſſarily follows; That there is now no ſuch thing in being, as a Power of granting Licences. Or had there been any ſuch Power before this new Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Rule was made, yet it was then taken away by the Pope, in decreeing, That <hi>the Command and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Roman Inquiſition, was to be inviolably obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> And leſt ſome perhaps might preſume to read the Bible, notwithſtanding the Penalty threatned to them that do ſo; to give check as much as might be to ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, the Bookſellers who ſhall ſell them to ſuch Perſons, beſides the loſs of the price of the Books, are liable to be puniſhed at the Biſhop's Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>It would be now ſuperfluous to produce Cardinal <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin, Sixtus Senenſis, Stapleton, Gretſer, Ledeſna, Azorius,</hi> or any other great Names in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as Witneſſes of this Practice. I ſhall therefore conclude with a brief Recollection of what hath been delivered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In the Pope's or the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Dominions, no Vulgar Tranſlation of the Bible is allowed; nor any Parcels or Summaries of the Bible, or of the Stories thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> In thoſe Countries where the Vulgar Bible is not abſolutely prohibited, no Man is allowed to read it without a Licence.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49460:9"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> This Licence muſt be granted by the Biſhop or Inquiſitor only; (though by the Cuſtom of <hi>France</hi> it may be granted by the Penitentiary or Curat.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> It may not be granted by them; to all Perſons who deſire it; but to thoſe only of whom they ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that they can receive no hurt by reading it; That is, thoſe of whom they are ſo ſecure, that they think there is no fear of loſing them; and few or none of theſe will ever deſire it. So that all this talk of granting leave to read the Bible amounts to no more than this, That thoſe who deſire it, ſhall for the moſt part be denied it. Even the Mareſchal of <hi>Chaſtres</hi>'s Lady, notwithſtanding her great Quality and Piety, could not without much difficulty get a Licence from the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Sens.</hi> Nor could ſhe by any Means procure it for the whole Bible, but for ſome certain Books only.
<note n="(o)" place="margin">Le San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaire fermè aux Profames. <hi>p.</hi> 339.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THat it is contrary to the Will of God, contrary to Reaſon, yea contrary to the Practice of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, for more than a thouſand Years after Chriſt, not to permit the free uſe of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the Vulgar.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>That it is the Will of God, That the Vulgar ſhould have the free uſe of the Scripture, omitting many other Arguments, theſe three alone may ſuffice to prove.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49460:9"/>
                     <item>1. That God cauſed it at firſt to be written in a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage underſtood by the Vulgar.</item>
                     <item>2. He cauſed it to be directed and addreſſed to them.</item>
                     <item>3. He commanded them to acquaint themſelves with it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. God cauſed the holy Scriptures to be at firſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in a Language underſtood by the Vulgar. That the Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets were written in the common Language of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is generally granted by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves. Monſieur <hi>Mallet</hi> indeed, has been ſo hardy as to ſay, That <hi>it is moſt probable, that the Books of the Law were not compoſed by</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Vulgar Language of the Jews.</hi> But the Arguments by which he attempts to prove it, are not only ridiculous, and in themſelves falſe; but in caſe they were true, would be ſo far from eſtabliſhing what he aſſerts, that they would quite deſtroy it: He that hath a Mind to ſee them expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, let him conſult Monſieur <hi>Arnaud</hi>'s (another learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Romaniſt)</hi> Confutation of his Book <note n="(b)" place="margin">De la Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture de l' E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criture Sainte contre les Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodoxes extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagans &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies de Monſ. <hi>Mallet.</hi>
                     </note>; Out of which I ſhall at preſent tranſcribe but one Paſſage. <hi>I ſhall ſay a Word only,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of</hi> Moſes<hi>'s laſt Song, becauſe it is a demonſtrative Proof, that there is nothing in the World more manifeſtly falſe, than that which Monſieur</hi> Mallet <hi>ſays is probable; for there is nothing in all the Books of</hi> Moſes, <hi>that is more nobly written, and in a more lofty Stile than this Song, which he commanded the Jews to write, and to learn by Heart, and to ſing often, that it might ſerve as a Teſtimony againſt themſelves, if they ſhould forſake the Worſhip of God. He therefore certainly ſuppoſed, that they would underſtand it, ſince his Intention was, that in ſinging it, they ſhould be touched and affected with it</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Je diray Seulement un mot de ſon dernier Cantique; parce que c'eſt une preuve demonſtrative pour faire voir que Mr. <hi>Mall.</hi> appelle probable la choſe du monde la plus viſiblement fauſſe, <hi>&amp;c. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 55.</note>.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49460:10"/>
                  <p> As for the Books of the New Teſtament, there is no queſtion (ſave of two only, the Goſpel of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> and the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews)</hi> but that they were all written in <hi>Greek,</hi> which was then the moſt Vulgar Language in the World, there being no other Tongue at that time underſtood by ſo many People. And whereas it is objected that the <hi>Latin</hi> was the Vulgar Tongue of the <hi>Romans,</hi> to whom notwithſtanding St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote in <hi>Greek:</hi> The anſwer is eaſy, That the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue was at that time more generally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and uſed at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf: It was more known to the Strangers there, and particularly to the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom the Apoſtle had in his Epiſtle a ſpecial regard to; who were well acquainted with the <hi>Greek,</hi> but for the moſt part ignorant of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue
<note n="d" place="margin">Grot. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in Evang. S. Marci &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Heb.</note>. And for the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves, ſcarce any could be found, no not among their Women, who did not underſtand it; In ſuch common uſe was it, that (as Mr. <hi>Arnaud</hi> obſerves) they taught it even their Parrots <note n="e" place="margin">De la Lect. <hi>&amp;c. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note>.</p>
                  <p>If St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel was written at firſt in <hi>Hebrew</hi> (as many of the Ancients affirm); by <hi>Hebrew</hi> they meant that which was then the Vulgar Language of the <hi>Jews</hi> who dwelt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for whoſe ſake his Goſpel was primarily written. This is aſſerted by ſuch great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>one would think</hi> no Romaniſt ſhould reject; particularly by <hi>Eſtius</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin.</hi> I ſhall recite <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Words, and for brevity ſake refer the Reader to <hi>Eſtius</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Eſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg. in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Epiſt. ad Hebraeos, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hac quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtione. Qua lingua ſcripta ſit Epiſt. ad Hebraeos.</note>.
<q>It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probable, ſays the Cardinal, that the Goſpel of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> and the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> were written in the <hi>Syriac</hi> Tongue, for <hi>Albertus Widmeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> and <hi>Guido Fabritius</hi> have proved it by the moſt convincing Arguments: Neither do the ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Irenaeus, Origen, Euſebius, Athanaſius, Epiphanius,</hi>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49460:10"/> 
                        <hi>Jerom,</hi> who ſay theſe Books (eſpecially the Goſpel of St. <hi>Matthew)</hi> were written in Hebrew, contradict theſe; for they ſpeak of that Hebrew which was the Vulgar Tongue in the time of the Apoſtles, even as in the Goſpel it ſelf we frequently read, that a thing was ſo call'd in the Hebrew, when it is manifeſt, that was ſo call'd in the Syriac: For inſtance, He went forth into a place call'd the place of a Scull, which is called in the Hebrew <hi>Golgotha;</hi> whereas <hi>Golgotha</hi> is not a proper Hebrew, but a Syriac word <note n="g" place="margin">Bell. <hi>de Verbo Dei,</hi> l. 2. c. 4.</note>.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Add to this, That <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſays expreſly, that St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> writ his Goſpel in his Country Language; and the reaſon he gives for it, neceſſarily required that he ſhould do ſo <note n="h" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſiaſt.</hi> l. 3.</note>.</p>
                  <p>For the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> it matters not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was originally written in Greek or Syriac, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both theſe Languages were then generally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the Hebrews: Tho <hi>Eſtius</hi> has produc'd ſuch Arguments as will not eaſily be anſwered, to prove that it was at firſt written in Greek. To conclude this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: Since God cauſed the Scriptures to be at firſt written in a Language the Vulgar were acquainted with, who can be ſo ſenſleſs as to imagine, that is was not his pleaſure that the vulgar ſhould read them?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. God at firſt addreſſed the Holy Scriptures to the Vulgar, as well as to others: <hi>I have written to him,</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>the great Things of my Law</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Hoſ. 8. 12.</note>. Who was he to whom he had written them? The Verſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going told us it was <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who is there put for the whole Body of the Iſraelites. The firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> is directed to all that in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Place call upon the Name of the Lord Jeſus. The ſecond, to the Church of God which is at <hi>Corinth,</hi> with all the Saints which are in all <hi>Acaia.</hi> For the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49460:11"/> reſt of the Epiſtles, I refer the Reader to the Diſcourſe quoted in the Margin <note n="(k)" place="margin">The Lay-Chriſtian's Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to read the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>. Now can any Man who has not quite loſt his Underſtanding ſuppoſe, that God would not have theſe Epiſtles read, by thoſe Perſons to whom they were written?</p>
                  <p>There are thoſe Perſons, I know, who pretend to think ſo; who tell us, That though St. <hi>Paul</hi> directed his Epiſtles to all Chriſtians in general, yet his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, that the Paſtors of the Church only ſhould read them. But can any thing be ſaid more abſurdly? Are not thoſe Epiſtles he deſigned for the Paſtors, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to them alone? as his Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus:</hi> Why then ſhould he direct his other Epiſtles to <hi>all</hi> the Saints, but that it was his intention, that they all ſhould be made acquainted with them? When his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians</hi> is directed to <hi>ALL the Saints at</hi> Philippi, <hi>together with the Biſhops and Deacons:</hi> Can any Man have the face to ſay, That he intended it only for the Biſhops and Deacons? Is it not as manifeſt, as that there are ſuch Epiſtles, that his Speech in them is uſually addreſſed to the People? And let a Man but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider, That in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> he commands, <hi>That after that Epiſtle had been read a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, they ſhould cauſe it to be read alſo in the Church of the</hi> Laodiceans <note n="(l)" place="margin">Coloſſ. 4. 16.</note>: That he gives a moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Charge, That his Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians ſhould be read to all the Holy Brethren</hi> 
                     <note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 27.</note>; and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, if he can, that it was his meaning, that the Scripture ſhould be withheld from any the pooreſt and moſt ignorant Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Nor has God only addreſſed the Holy Scriptures to the Vulgar, but he hath alſo commanded them to acquaint themſelves familiarly with them. <hi>The words I command thee this day,</hi> ſaith God to all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (Prieſts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49460:11"/> and People) <hi>ſhall be in thine Heart, and thou ſhalt teach them diligently to thy Children, and talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thine Houſe,</hi> &amp;c.
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Deut. 6. 6, 7, 8.</note> Can it be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that they ſhould talk of theſe words, when they ſate in their Houſes, and when they walked by the way, when they lay down, and when they roſe up; that they ſhould bind them for a Sign upon their Hands, and that they ſhould be as Frontlets between their eyes; that they ſhould write them upon the Poſts of their Houſes, and upon their Gates; that they ſhould teach them diligently to their Children, and yet ſhould not be permitted to read them? When <hi>Moſes</hi> had made an end of ſpeaking theſe words, having ſaid all that he had in charge from God to deliver to this People, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes thus: <hi>Set your Hearts unto all the words which I te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify among you this day, which ye ſhall command your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to obſerve and do, all the words of this Law; for it is not a vain thing for you, becauſe it is your Life,</hi> &amp;c.
<note n="(o)" place="margin">Deut. 32. 45, 46, 47.</note>. Is this ſaid like a Man; that would not have them ſo much as read the words he had ſpoken to them?</p>
                  <p>And for the New Teſtament, the Command is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to Chriſtians of all States and Qualities, That <hi>the Word of Chriſt dwell in them;</hi> and not only ſo, but that it dwell in them <hi>richly;</hi> ſo richly, that they may thereby be indowed <hi>with all Wiſdom</hi>
                     <note n="(p)" place="margin">Coloſſ. 3. 16.</note>. Which St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> thought ſo plain a Command to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People to read the Scriptures, that in his Sermon upon theſe words, he thus earneſtly exhorts them; <hi>Hearken all ye that are Men of the VVorld, and have a VVife and Children under your Government, how even You he commands eſpecially to read the Scriptures; and that not ſimply, or now and then by chance, but with much dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi>
                     <note n="(q)" place="margin">Hom. 9. <hi>in Epiſt. ad</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ.</note>. If St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s word be not thought ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent, I ſhall add to it a late famous Divine of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49460:12"/> Church of <hi>Rome. VVhat more clear,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>than that St.</hi> Paul <hi>thus exhorts,</hi> Coloſſ. 3. <hi>Let the VVord of Chriſt dwell in You. But in what You? In thoſe Saints and Faithful Brethren in Chriſt that were at</hi> Coloſſe, <hi>to whom he inſcribed this Epiſtle, (not as ſome other Epiſtles to Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons); Let the VVord of Chriſt therefore dwell in You in all Wiſdom,</hi> &amp;c.
<note n="r" place="margin">Eſpenſ. <hi>in Epiſt. ad</hi> Tit. <hi>cap.</hi> 2 <hi>p.</hi> 518, 519.</note>. Which the Author ſpeaks to ſhew, that the reading of the Scriptures ought not to be prohibited to Lay-men. That this Prohibition is indeed contrary to the Will of God, will yet further appear, by ſhewing that it is very abſurd and unreaſonable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let us hear what common Reaſon ſaith,</hi> (to uſe the words of a Reverend Perſon of our own Church, in an excellent Treatiſe upon this Subject) <hi>and that teaches us, That ſince the Holy Scriptures were written for the uſe and benefit of all, all ſhould have the liberty to read them. They were written for all, it is plain; for that which they teach is the Duty of all, that which they promiſe is the Portion of all</hi> 
                     <note n="s" place="margin">
                        <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> p. 58.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Dare any one ſay, That the Scripture was not given as a Rule to the People? That it was not deſigned to teach them, not only what they are concerned to <hi>know</hi> and to <hi>do</hi> in the general as they are <hi>Men,</hi> or as they are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but to inſtruct them alſo more particularly, how they ought to demean themſelves in their ſeveral Callings and Relations, in their different States and Conditions of Life, that they may walk worthy of God in this World, and be made meet for the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the next? And what can be more abſurd, than that a Man ſhould not be ſuffered to read thoſe Leſſons,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49460:12"/> which as he hopes for Salvation, he is bound to learn? That he ſhould not be permitted the peruſal of thoſe Laws, which under peril of Damnation he is bound to obey? That he ſhould be forbid to ſee with his own Eyes, what God hath promiſed to quicken him to his Duty; and what he hath threatned to deter him from the contrary?</p>
                  <p>Are not the Scriptures (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> calls them) the Weapons of our Spiritual Warfare, the Storehouſe of Spiritual Medicines <note n="t" place="margin">Hom. 9. in Epiſt. ad Coloſ.</note>? Are they not given for a Light to our Feet and a Lamp to our Paths
<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 105. Prov. 6. 23.</note>? And therefore to deprive the People of them, what is it elſe, but to take away the Light from a Man in darkneſs? To deny Medicines to one that is ſick? Or to deprive a Souldier of thoſe Weapons, by which he ſhould defend himſelf, and repel his Enemies? What the the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſays in oppoſition to this ſhall be anon conſidered.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall add no more upon this Head, than what I ſhall borrow from ſome great and learned Men of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Biſhop of <hi>Vence</hi> in his Dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Epiſtle prefixed to his Tranſlation of the New Teſt. addreſſes thus to all Chriſtians indifferently: <hi>Behold it is the Teſtament of the Son of God, your Father and your Judg, which I offer to you: I cannot doubt but the reading of it will be acceptable to you. You will ſee that he hath there left you a Patrimony moſt divine, which is his Truth; and that he hath divided it in a wonderful manner: For though it be but one, yet he hath ſuited it to the condition, and to the Duties of every Man, to the end that all Men by practiſing its Precepts, may live in Peace, and may come to the poſſeſſion of his Inheritance, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Voicy le Teſtament du Fils de Dieu voſtre Pere et voſtre Juge, que je Vous offre. Je ne puis douter que la lecture ne vous en ſoit agreable. Vous verrez qu' il vous y laiſſe un pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie tout divin, qui eſt ſa Verite &amp;c.</note>.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49460:13"/>
                  <p> The Tranſlators of the <hi>Mons</hi> Teſtament in their Preface have theſe Words: <hi>If God heretofore commanded his People to read that Law without ceaſing, which he had given them, and to meditate in it day and night. And if the Religious believe themſelves obliged to read perpetually, the Rule they have received from their Founder. How can we neglect to read the Law of Jeſus Chriſt, the words of which are Spirit and Life? ſince being entred by Baptiſm into the Catholick and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, of which Jeſus Chriſt is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we ought to look upon the Goſpel as our Rule, which teaches us his Will, which aſſures us of his Promiſes, which is our Light in this World, and which muſt one Day be our Judg</hi> 
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Que ſi Dieu avoit commandé autrefois à ſon peuple de lire ſans ceſſe la loy qu' il luy avoit donnée et de la mediter jour it nuit; et ſi les Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eux ſe croient obligez de lire tous les jours la Regle qu' ils ont recüe de leur Inſtituteur: comment pouvonsnous neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liger de lire la loy de Jeſus Chriſt &amp;c <hi>p.</hi> 4, 5.</note>? In the Judgment of theſe Learned Men of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to deny the reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the People, is as unreaſonable and unjuſt, as not to ſuffer an Heir to ſee his Father's Will, or to forbid the Regulars the ſight of their Rule.</p>
                  <p>If any Man ſhall think that theſe Teſtimonies are not weighty enough, I ſhall add another, which cannot be refuſed by thoſe Men I now diſpute againſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great: <hi>The holy Scripture,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as a kind of Looking-glaſs is ſet before the Eyes of our Mind, that our inward Face may be ſeen by it. By it we know what in us is foul and what is fair; by it we perceive how much we profit; by it how far we are from profiting. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the brave Exploits of the Saints, and provokes the weak to the imitation of them; and while it commemorates their victorious Acts, it confirms and ſtrengthens our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt the aſſaults of Vice, and we are the leſs fearful in the Encounter, by ſeeing the foregoing Triumphs of ſo many valiant Men. But ſometimes it ſets before us not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49460:13"/> 
                     <hi>their Virtues but their Falls, that in the Victory of the ſtrong, we may find that which we ought to imitate, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in their Falls, that which we ought to fear</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Scriptura ſacra mentis oculis quaſi quoddam ſpeculum opponitur, ut interna noſtra facies in ipſa videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Expoſ. Moral in 1 cap. Job l. 2. c. 1. fol. 4. K</note>. I appeal now to the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves, Whether this great Pope, thought it not fit, that the reading of the Holy Scriptures ſhould be left free to every Man? If they ſay no; I queſtion not but to make them confeſs it whether they will or no, in the following parts of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>Nor is the practice of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church now, leſs contrary to the practice of the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, for more than a thouſand Years after Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>That the Scriptures lay open to all ſorts of Perſons in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, I need not prove; It is ſufficiently known by that Paſſage of <hi>Joſephus</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Joſeph. l. 2. contr. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion.</note> frequently quoted by Proteſtant Writers, viz. <hi>That if any Man ask a Jew concerning the Laws, he will tell him every thing more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily than his Name; for learning them as ſoon as they come to have ſence of any thing, they retain them deeply imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their Minds.</hi> And <hi>Maimonides</hi> informs us, That it did not ſuffice a <hi>Jew,</hi> barely to read the Law; but he was to write it too. For tho a Father had left his Son a Copy of the Law, he was notwithſtanding obliged to write for himſelf, another Copy with his own Hand; or procure it to be written, if he could not write him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And therefore the Pentateuch at leaſt (as <hi>Morinus</hi> a Learned <hi>Romaniſt</hi> infers)
<note n="b" place="margin">Exercit. Bibl. l. 2. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit. 16. c. 1. n. 6, 7.</note> that is the Books of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> were in the Hands of all the <hi>Jews;</hi> and frequently many Copies were in one Family, becauſe they were wont to keep thoſe that were left by their Fathers.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49460:14"/>
                  <p> But my deſign at preſent, is to ſhew, That the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church (yea of the Roman Church it ſelf heretofore) was quite contrary to the Rules and Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now: And that this may be made ſo evident, that thoſe who wiſh it were falſe may be conſtrain'd to confeſs it: I ſhall proceed in the ſame Method, that a Reverend Author hath done in a late learned Diſcourſe upon another controverted Point <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>A Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> &amp;c.</note>; <hi>viz.</hi> I ſhall prove by unqueſtionable Teſtimonies, for twelve hundred Years downward, from our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Birth, that the reading of the Scripture had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint put upon it, but was left in common to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
                  <p>That it was ſo in the firſt Age, we have undeniable Evidence in the Scripture it ſelf. Would our Saviour and his Apoſtles in their popular Diſcourſes, ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſent their Hearers to the Scriptures, had they not then been allowed to read them
<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 21. 13. Luk. 6. 3, 4. Joh. 10. 34, 35. Act. 2. 16.</note>? Could the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> have ſearched the Scriptures, to ſee whether thoſe things that were ſpoken by <hi>Paul</hi> were ſo <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 17. 11.</note>, had not the Scripture been in their Hands? Had not all the Saints in all <hi>Achaia</hi> been permitted to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, could St. <hi>Paul</hi> have ſaid truly to them, <hi>We write none other things to you than what you read</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 13.</note>? That ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Text ſo frequently produced by Romiſh Writers, to prove that the Vulgar ought not to read the Scriptures
<note n="g" place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 16.</note>, is an Argument that in the Apoſtles time they did ſo: For it is not eaſie to conceive, how <hi>the unlearned and unſtable ſhould wreſt the Scriptures,</hi> had they never read them.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame Age, in St. <hi>Clement</hi>'s Epiſtle directed to all the Chriſtians at <hi>Corinth,</hi> we find theſe Words: <hi>You have known Beloved, you have well known the holy Scriptures, you have thoroughly looked into the Oracles of God,</hi> &amp;c.
<note n="h" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49460:14"/> And if the Chriſtians at <hi>Corinth</hi> were ſo converſant in the Scriptures, ſurely the Chriſtians of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the time of this Biſhop, were not forbidden to read them.</p>
                  <p>Toward the end of the ſecond Age, <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> gives this Character of a Chriſtian; <hi>His whole Life is a holy Solemnity, his Sacrifices are Prayers and Praiſes, and conferences of the Scriptures before his Meal, and Pſalms and Hymns while he is at it</hi> 
                     <note n="i" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Stromat. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 728. Edit. 1629.</note>. Certainly no Reſtraint was then laid upon the reading of the Scripture, when it was the common Practice of Chriſtians to read it, and make it the matter of their Diſcourſe at their Meals.</p>
                  <p>For the third Century (tho many other Witneſſes ſtand ready, yet) <hi>Origen</hi> alone may ſuffice. Whether we conſider, 1. How early he himſelf was educated in the Scriptures: Or 2. What he hath left on record to this purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, His Father <hi>Leonides</hi> before he put him to other Learning, put him upon the ſtudy of the Scriptures, of which he ſet him a daily Task, to learn by heart
<note n="k" place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſiaſt. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 2,</note>. Now his Father being a Lay-man, and he himſelf then a Child (for the Father was crown'd with Martyrdom, before the Son was ſeventeen years old) what <hi>Arnaud</hi> hence infers, undeniably follows <hi>viz.</hi> That the Church then thought it good, not only for Lay-men to read the Scriptures, but to make their Children alſo read them in their tender Age.</p>
                  <p>2. Of thoſe many Paſſages which <hi>Arnaud</hi> and others have obſerved in his Writings, it will be ſufficient to produce one: directing his Speech to all Chriſtians with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction he thus exhorts them: <hi>We beſeech you not to content your ſelves to hear the Word of God, when</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49460:15"/> 
                     <hi>read in the Church, but to apply your ſelves to it at home, and to meditate upon it day and night; for Jeſus Chriſt is there preſent as well as in the Church, and they that ſeek him ſhall find him every where. Therefore he hath commanded us to meditate in the Law of the Lord, when we walk by the way, and when we ſit in our Houſes, when we lye down, and when we riſe up</hi> 
                     <note n="(l)" place="margin">Hom. 9. in Levit.</note>.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the fourth Age, it is certain that the Bible was in Lay-mens hands, becauſe in <hi>Diocleſian</hi>'s Perſecution, many Lay-men, to ſave themſelves, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up their Bibles to be burnt <note n="(m)" place="margin">Quid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorem Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, qui tunc in Eccleſia nulla fuerant dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſuffulti? <hi>&amp;c. Optat. adverſ. Parmen. l.</hi> 1.</note>.</p>
                  <p>That in the ſucceeding Parts of that Age, under the Chriſtian Emgots, they had the free uſe of them is as manifeſt; becauſe we find that all ſorts of People were frequently and earneſtly preſſed by their Teachers to read them.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not inſiſt upon what is by others produc'd out of St. <hi>Jerom, viz.</hi> The Dedication of his Commentaries upon the Scriptures to Women, his Epiſtles to many of that Sex, in which he highly commends them for their ſtudy of the Scriptures, and exhorts them diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſtruct their Children therein: How he adviſed <hi>Gaudentius</hi> to cauſe his Daughter at ſeven years old to get the Pſalms by Heart, and when ſhe ſhould come to the age of twelve, to treaſure up in her Heart the Books of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Goſpels, the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, and the Prophets. But (omitting theſe) I think it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to tell you, that even Father <hi>Thomaſſin</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, that this Father moſt ſtraitly charged, not only the Clergy and the Religious (that is, Monks and Nuns) to read the Scriptures; but recommended the reading of them to all ſorts of Perſons, without diſtinction of Age or Sex, even to Women and Girls <note n="(n)" place="margin">Part. 1. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>n.</hi> 6.</note>. What pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence then have the Papiſts, for quoting St. <hi>Jerom</hi> as one
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49460:15"/> of their ſide? You ſhall hear. In his Epiſtle to <hi>Paulinus</hi> he complains, That whereas Men of all other Arts contain'd themſelves within the bounds of their own Profeſſion, every one took upon him to be a Teacher of the Scriptures, even the <hi>doting old Man, and the tatling old Wife,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(o)" place="margin">Quod Medicorum eſt prómittunt Medici, tractant fabrilia Fabri; Sola Scripturarum ars eſt quam ſibi paſſim omnes vendicant.—hanc garrula anus, hunc delirus ſenex, &amp;c.</note> an unanſwerable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that the moſt ſimple of both Sexes did then freely read the Scriptures; For could they preſume to <hi>teach</hi> them, had they never <hi>read</hi> them? Nor doth he blame their <hi>reading</hi> them, but that they took upon them to be Teachers, before they themſelves had learnt them; <hi>docent antequam diſcant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How vehement and copious St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is, in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to his Hearers, of all Ranks and Qualities, to read the Scriptures, you may be inform'd by another Learned Papiſt
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Eſpenc. Comment. in Epiſt. ad Tit. c. 2. p. 517. Ed. Pariſ. 1619.</note>. I ſhall give but a taſte: <hi>It may not ſuffice,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that You hear the Divine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures read in the Churches; but in Your Houſes, either read them Your ſelves, or get others to read, and do You rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily hearken to them. Hear the Divine Scriptures read in the Church, as You are wont, and read them over again at Home. If any be ſo employ'd, that before his repaſt, he cannot have leiſure, let it not grieve him, to read ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them at his Meal; that as the Body is fed with Meat, ſo the Soul may be refreſh'd with the Words of God; that the whole Man, both outward and inward, may ariſe ſatisfied from a holy and wholſom Banquet,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(q)" place="margin">De Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Serm. 55, 56, 57. De San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis Serm. 38.</note>.</p>
                  <p>What the ſame learned Romaniſt, hath to the ſame purpoſe produc'd out of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> if the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter pleaſe to read, methinks it ſhould put him to the bluſh. I ſhall only obſerve, That this incomparable Saint, makes the reading of the Scriptures, not only neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for all Men, of whatſoever rank they be, but more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49460:16"/> neceſſary for thoſe whoſe Buſineſs lies in the midſt of the World, than for thoſe who live more retired from it. As you may ſee by many pregnant Proofs, in that excellent Treatiſe before mention'd <note n="(s)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> p. 40</note>.</p>
                  <p>Tho I omit many, as St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> &amp;c. yet I ſhall mention two more Witneſſes in this Age; The firſt, is <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> who derides the Chriſtians for breeding up their Children in the knowledg of the Scriptures. The ſecond, is St. <hi>Cyril</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who in his Catechiſms for the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate, (that is, Perſons newly baptiz'd) charges them to read all the Books both of the Old and New Teſtament, and diligently to meditate upon them
<note n="(t)" place="margin">Catecheſ. 4. de Sacra. Script. <hi>p.</hi> 36, 37, 38. Edit. Par. 1640.</note>.</p>
                  <p>In the fifth Age, <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in his Books againſt <hi>Julian,</hi> informs us. That it was then alſo the practice of Chriſtians, not barely to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelves, but to train up their Children in them. And in anſwer to the Apoſtate's ſcurrilous Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, he ſhews what Advantages accru'd to them by being early inſtructed in the Divine Scripture, above all that could be expected from the Learning of the Greeks <note n="(u)" place="margin">Lib. 7. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Julianum.</note>.</p>
                  <p>In the ſixth Age, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, in a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Sermon, thus exhorts his Hearers: <hi>Study, moſt dear Brethren, the Words of God. Do not deſpiſe the Letters our Maker hath ſent us. It is a great advantage, that by them the Soul is quicken'd, leſt it ſhould be benumn'd with the cold of its iniquity. When we there ſee, that Juſt Men have done valiantly, we our ſelves are diſpoſed to cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in well-doing. The Soul of the Reader is enkindled by the Flame of Holy Examples. It ſees their noble Acts, and is diſpleaſed with it ſelf, that it doth not imitate them. Hence in the Voice of the Bridgroom it is ſaid to the Bride, Thy Neck is like the Tower of</hi> David, <hi>builded for an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory;</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49460:16"/> 
                     <hi>whereon there hang a thouſand Bucklers. In the Neck is the Throat, in the Throat is the Voice; What therefore is meant by the Neck of Holy Church, but its Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oracles, whereon a thouſand Shields are ſaid to hang, becauſe all our defence is contained in the Sacred Oracles. For there are the Commandments of God, there are the Examples of Juſt Men. If the Soul grow cold in the love of God, let it hear what is ſaid; Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Mind, and with all thy Strength,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(w)" place="margin">Hom. 16. Super Ezech.</note> He that deſires to ſee more to this purpoſe, let him conſult his moral Expoſition of the Book of <hi>Job,</hi> (eſpecially <hi>l.</hi> 20.); his Epiſtle to <hi>Leander</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Sevil,</hi> and read his famous Story of Poor <hi>Servolus</hi> 
                     <note n="(x)" place="margin">Hom. 15. de diverſ. Lect. Evangelii.</note>. And when he has done ſo, I ſhall leave him to judg, whether this great Pope was of the ſame judgment with Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV, and the <hi>Trent</hi> Fathers? Whether the Holy Scriptures were not in his time read at <hi>Rome,</hi> by the moſt unlearned Vulgar?</p>
                  <p>For the ſeventh Age, <hi>Iſidore</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Sevil,</hi> is a Witneſs beyond exception: <hi>The Holy Scripture,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to the weak, and thoſe that are Children in underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as to its Hiſtory, ſeems low in words; when to more excellent Men it riſes higher, while it opens to them its My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and by this means it remains common, both to the little Ones and to the Perfect. The Holy Scripture is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in proportion to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of every Reader; as Manna, which to the ancient People gave a different taſte, acccording to their different Palats,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(y)" place="margin">Scriptura Sacra infirmis &amp; ſenſu par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>is ſecundum hiſtoriam humilis videtur in Verbis; cum excellentioribus autem viris al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s incedit dum eis ſua myſteria pandit, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> per hoc utriſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> manet communis, &amp; parvulis &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erfectis Sententiar. l. 1. c. 18.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49460:17"/>
                  <p> That the ſame practice continu'd in the eighth Age, we are aſſured by venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> and the Saxon Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. In his Character of <hi>Aidan</hi> Biſhop of the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumbrians,</hi> he makes it none of the leaſt of his Vertues, <hi>That he was ſo far from the ſloth of the Age, that all that went with him, whether Clergy or Lay-men, were obliged to meditate, that is, to take pains to read the Scriptures, or to learn the Pſalms. This,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was his daily Work, and the Work of all thoſe that were with him</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. l. 3. c. 5.</note>.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe the reading of the Scriptures was then too generally neglected, the Saxon Church endeavoured a Remedy for this Evil in her Homilies; out of which I ſhall cite but one Paſſage, <hi>viz. The reading of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, purges the Soul of the Reader. It brings to mind the fear of eternal Puniſhment; it alſo lifts up his Heart to the Joy Above. Whoſoever would be together with God, he ought to pray often, and often to read the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures; for when we pray, we ſpeak to God, and when we read the Holy Bible, God ſpeaks to us. The reading of the Holy Bible brings a double benefit to the Readers: The firſt, That it informs the Mind; the other, That it takes it off from the Trifles of this World, to the love of God.</hi> How far was the Church yet from believing, That Lay-mens reading of the Scriptures, <hi>did more hurt than good.</hi> He that hath a mind to ſee more out of the Saxon Homilies, let him conſult the Notes on <hi>Bede</hi>'s <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Hiſtory</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Lib. 3. p. 172, 173, 174. l. 4. p. 310.</note>.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>9th</hi> Age, <hi>Rabanus Maurus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> ſpeaks thus: <hi>That Divine Wiſdom which ſhines forth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Holy Spripture, is both to the Strong and Weak, both to the Wiſe and Fooliſh, if they will mind it, and truly obey it, a wholſom Medicine. It is the enlightning of the Mind, the Correction of Life, the Path of Righteouſneſs. And</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49460:17"/> 
                     <hi>therefore both the greater and the leſſer, do want its help, and ſtand ſtand in need of its conduct</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Sapientia Divina quae in Sacra Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra elucet, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus tam potentibus quam infirmis, tam ſapientibus quam inſipientibus, ſi eam recte intende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, &amp; ei rite obedierint, Medicina Salubris eſt. Ipſa eſt Illuminatio animae, &amp;c.</note>.</p>
                  <p>In the tenth, <hi>Odo</hi> Abbat of <hi>Clugny</hi> tells us; That <hi>by the wild Goats which God ſpeaks of to</hi> Job, <hi>are meant all good and wiſe Men. For as theſe Goats abide in the Rocks, and if they at any time fall from their Heights, they keep themſelves unhurt in their Fleſh: So theſe good Men dwell in the Rocks, becauſe they endeavour to live according to the Examples of the Fathers; and when they fall at any time, they are not daſhed in pieces, becauſe leaning upon the Scriptures of the two Teſtaments, they eſcape, and by the comfort of them, ſuſtain themſelves, that they do not faint in trouble</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Collat. l. 3.</note>. It ſeems, the Scriptures were yet thought uſeful to every Man, to ſupport and comfort him in Troubles and Afflictions.</p>
                  <p>In the eleventh Age, hear what Advice <hi>Theophylact</hi> gives to Parents: <hi>If thou wilt have thy Children obey thee, inſtruct them in the Word of God; ſay not, that it belongs only to Monks to read the Scriptures, for it is the Duty of every Chriſtian; eſpecially of thoſe who are converſant in the World, who ſtand in need of greater Aſſiſtances, as Men toſſed in a Storm. 'Tis thy Concern and Intereſt, that they hear the Scriptures, for they will thence learn to honour their Father and Mother</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Theoph. in Epheſ. c. 6. v. 4.</note>. So far was this great Biſhop from thinking the reading of the Scriptures hurtful to the Laity, that he thought it more neceſſary for them, than others; ſo far from confining them only to the Learned, that he would have Children, the moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Laity, to read them.</p>
                  <p>In the twelfth Age, <hi>Rupertus Tuitienſis</hi> ſays; <hi>That the Holy Scripture is rightly called a Field, becauſe it is in</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49460:18"/> 
                     <hi>truth a publick thing, that lies open, and is propos'd to all Men who are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to read or hear it</hi> 
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Sancta Scriptura recte dicitur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, quia profecto res publica eſt, res in aperto poſita, &amp; cunctis hominibus, imò populis omnibus legere vel audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re capientibus propoſita eſt. L. 1. de Glorific. Trinit.</note>. To whom we may add St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who in a popular Diſcourſe earneſtly exhorts his Hearers, to apply themſelves to the Scriptures, from the conſideration of thoſe ineſtimable Benefits they would receive thereby <note n="f" place="margin">Serm. 24. de diverſis.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have ſhew'd the practice of the Chriſtian Church to the twelfth Age; not from the Teſtimonies of obſcure and ſuſpected Authors, but of Men famous in their Generations, and whoſe Names are held in great veneration in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Which I have the rather done, becauſe ſome Perſons have had the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to bear the World in hand, that in the Primitive Church, a reſtraint was laid upon the reading of the Scripture. An Aſſertion ſo manifeſtly untrue, that we need deſire no clearer Proofs of the contrary, than thoſe two or three Paſſages out of the Ancients, they produce for it.</p>
                  <p>If the Reader deſire to know, when, and upon what occaſion this Liberty was firſt taken from Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I'll now tell him. The firſt Synodical Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was that of the Synod of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> in the Year 1228, in theſe words: <hi>We forbid that Lay-men be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have the Books of the Old and New Teſtament; unleſs perhaps ſome one out of Devotion, deſire to have the Pſalter or Breviary for Divine Offices, and the Hours of the Bleſſed Virgin; but even thoſe now mentioned, they may not have tranſlated in the vulgar Tongue.</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Prohibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus etiam ne Libros Veteris &amp; Novi Teſtamenti Laici permittantur habere; niſi forte Pſalterium aut Breviarium pro Divinis Officiis. ac horas Beatae Virginis aliquis ex devotione habere velit: Sed ne pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> libros habeant in vulgari Tranſlatos. D'Achetii, Tom. 2. p. 624.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49460:18"/>
                  <p> The ſpecial occaſion of this Decree, was the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>VValdenſes;</hi> who taught, that in Articles of Faith, the Holy Scripture was the Rule, by which Men were to judg, that whatſoever was not agreeable to the Word of God, ought to be rejected. That the reading and knowledg of the Scripture, was free and neceſſary to all Men, both Laity and Clergy <note n="*" place="margin">Cent. 12. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. Hiſt. c. 8.</note>. By this time the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had gotten ſuch a new Faith, as would not abide the old Teſt; and therefore it was prudently done, to deprive the People of the Scripture, that they might not be able to diſcover thoſe Errors into which they led them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>LET us now ſee what the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> offers, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify this Practice of the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo manifeſtly repugnant to Scripture, to Reaſon, and to the ancient Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf; yea, of the whole Chriſtian Church throughout the World.</p>
               <p>Surely, they muſt be very weighty Reaſons, or elſe they will never bear down ſo great a weight, as lies in the other Scale againſt them. Does he ſhew, that God hath retracted his firſt Grant? That he hath repealed his old Law, and eſtabliſhed one quite contrary in the room of it? Does he ſhew, That the Reaſon of the Thing is changed? So that if the Primitive Fathers were alive again, they would now with as much ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs diſſuade Lay-men from reading the Scripture, as they formerly exhorted them to it? Had he done thus, he had ſpoken to the purpoſe: But, alas! we
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49460:19"/> find nothing of this, nor any thing like it.</p>
               <p>What then are his Reaſons? You ſhall now hear: And I ſhall endeavour to repreſent them to the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, without abating one grain of their juſt weight. They are all reducible to this one general Head, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> that ariſe from the <hi>promiſcuous</hi> reading of the Scripture; ſeveral of which he mentions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts upon; and then acquaints us with the Reaſons (as he ſuppoſes) of thoſe Miſchiefs. That therefore my Diſcourſe upon them may be the more clear and diſtinct, I ſhall divide it into theſe three parts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I ſhall conſider the General Reaſon.</item>
                  <item>2. The Particulars he inſiſts upon.</item>
                  <item>3. The Reaſons he gives why theſe Miſchiefs flow from the free reading of the Bible.</item>
               </list>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>The general Reaſon he gives of this Reſtraint, is; The <hi>Miſchieſs</hi> that ariſe from the <hi>promiſcuous</hi> reading of the <hi>Bible: ſince theſe, and infinite other Miſchiefs ariſe from the free permitting the Bible among the Multitude, He (viz.</hi> the Papiſt) <hi>thinks it commendable in his Church, out of a true</hi> ſolicitude <hi>for the Salvation of Souls, to prevent thoſe Evils, by teaching the true ſenſe of this Sacred Volume—without leaving the Book to be ſcann'd by them as they pleaſe; and ſo not permitting them to turn the Food of their Souls into Poiſon, or abuſe that to their Deſtruction, which was ordain'd by Chriſt for their gaining of Heaven</hi>
                     <note n="(h)" place="margin">Chap. 7. p. 52.</note>. But if out of pure kindneſs to the Souls of the Vulgar, they take away this <hi>dangerous</hi> Book from them; Why do they give them other very perilous Books in the room of it? I mean <hi>Images</hi> (which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49460:19"/> they call Lay-mens Books) tho by the Confeſſion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their own Writers, they are horribly abuſed by the Vulgar. But to paſs that;</p>
                  <p>This is the Argument they commonly inſiſt upon, and tho it hath been wretchedly bafled again and again, yet for want of a better, it is upon every occaſion dreſs'd up anew, and urged with as brisk a Confidence, as if it had never before been heard of.</p>
                  <p>He ſays he <hi>does ſincerely, reſpect, honour and reverence the Scripture</hi>
                     <note n="(i)" place="margin">Chap. 6. p. 44.</note>. But methinks he expreſſes his <hi>reſpect</hi> and <hi>reverence,</hi> as untowardly, as the <hi>Lindians</hi> did to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their God <hi>Hercules,</hi> whom they worſhipped by throwing Stones at him. For what is this, but to ſay, that the Bible is the moſt dangerous Book in the World? ſince a Lay-man cannot read it, without danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eternally undone by it: And if this be to <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> the Scripture, I know not what it is to <hi>revile</hi> it.</p>
                  <p>The Repreſenter will ſay this is a <hi>falſe Inference.</hi> I ſhall be glad if he can make that appear, for nothing ſeems to follow more naturally from the Premiſes. He will ſay, he does not impute theſe <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> to the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf,</hi> but to Mens <hi>Abuſe</hi> of it <note n="(k)" place="margin">Chap. 7. p. 52.</note>. What then? the danger is not the leſs, if it be ſo apt to be abuſed, that ſcarce any Man can read it who will not ſo abuſe it. Let us ſuppoſe there are two things, the one of which is an excellent Antidote, if rightly uſed, but ſo hard a matter it is ſo to uſe it, that not one in an hundred can be found, to whom it doth not turn to Poyſon: The other is it ſelf a rank Poyſon, yet may be ſo temper'd, and taken with that caution, that it may become an Antidote: Is not now this Antidote (however excellent in it ſelf) as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous as the Poyſon?</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49460:20"/>
                  <p> But if theſe Miſchiefs proceed meerly from Mens <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe</hi> of Scripture, why is it then denied to thoſe who do not thus abuſe it? For in that he ſays, <hi>Such as for the MOST PART are not capable of reading it as they ought, have not leave to read it; and thoſe that are capable may have IN MOST CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTRIES leave to read it, as they pleaſe</hi> 
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Pag. 52.</note>. He plainly grants, that <hi>Some</hi> have not leave to read it, who are capable of reading it as they ought, and that <hi>in ſome Countries</hi> they cannot obtain this leave, tho they never ſo much deſire it. Where, by <hi>capable of reading as they ought,</hi> he muſt (if he ſpeak ſenſe) mean thoſe who will not abuſe it; tho it is a great miſtake to confound theſe two, as if they were the ſame, when they are as different, the one from the other, as a ſick Man is from one that is not capable of being well; and therefore to ſay that a Man who <hi>abuſes</hi> the Scripture, is not <hi>capable</hi> of reading it as he ought, is as abſurd, as that a ſick Man is not capable of recovering his Health. Were indeed all thoſe that abuſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture uncapable of reading it to good purpoſe, I ſhould not deny, but they might with good reaſon be deprived of it: But if they muſt be denied it for no other reaſon but becauſe they abuſe it; then let all Men be deprived of their Eyes, their Ears, their Tongues <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Man by whom theſe are not more or leſs abuſed: Yea let not only ſome, but every Man in the World, be denied the reading of the Scripture; becauſe (I fear) there is ſcarce any Man who is moſt careful to avoid it, but he may ſome time or other, through weakneſs or ignorance abuſe it.</p>
                  <p>It is therefore certain, that a Man ought not for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Abuſe to be deprived of this Priviledg: And if for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe mentioned by the Repreſenter, our bleſſed Saviour and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were much to blame, who put
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49460:20"/> all Men indifferently upon the ſtudy of the Scripture, notwithſtanding all <hi>theſe Abuſes</hi> were as high in their time, as they have been in any Age ſince. Did I ſay <hi>not for every Abuſe?</hi> I will add, not for <hi>any Abuſe,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there can be <hi>any</hi> that God did not foreſee; for ſince notwithſtanding <hi>any ſuch Abuſe,</hi> he gave free liberty to all Men, who can deny it to any, unleſs they will take upon them to correct God?</p>
                  <p>And yet when all is done; in caſe Men are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the reading of the Scripture, becauſe they abuſe it; then thoſe above all others ought to be denied it, who moſt extragavantly abuſe it. I mean thoſe, who prove the <hi>Pope</hi> is as much greater than the Emperor, as the Sun is greater than the Moon, from <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 16. <hi>God made two great Lights, the greater Light to rule the Day, and the leſſer Light to rule the Night.</hi> That in the Churches Power are two Swords, the Temporal and the Spiritual; from that Speech of St. <hi>Peter</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>Behold, here are two Swords.</hi> That the <hi>Pope</hi> is an abſolute univerſal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign; becauſe Chriſt ſaid to St. <hi>Peter, Feed my Sheep.</hi> That a married Man cannot pleaſe God, becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>They that are in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God.</hi> And to give one Inſtance in the Subject we are now upon; That no unlearned Man may preſume to meddle with the Scripture, becauſe God commanded, <hi>That if a Beaſt touch'd the Mountain, it ſhould be ſtoned, or thruſt through with a Dart.</hi> Did ever Men more abuſe the Scripture than thoſe, who for bad purpoſes put ſuch abſurd ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Senſes upon it? And yet theſe are the Men, who have taken upon them to be the only infallible Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it. Let all impartial Men then judg, who beſt deſerves to be forbidden to read it, Whether his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> or an honeſt <hi>Mechanic?</hi> The Truth is, the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Clergy have ſet up a Worldly Religion, ſo directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49460:21"/> to that of Chriſt, that the <hi>Heretical Scriptures,</hi> however <hi>tortured,</hi> will never be brought to a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with. The <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> they talk of that ariſe from the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> are but pretended; the <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> that come to <hi>themſelves</hi> thereby, are thoſe they are indeed afraid of; as was plainly confeſſed to Pope <hi>Julius</hi> III, by thoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops aſſembled at <hi>Bononia</hi> to conſult about the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Roman Church <note n="m" place="margin">Verger. Conſil. de Rom. Eccleſ. ſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda.</note>.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not inſiſt upon it, That the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent upon the <hi>Miſchiefs,</hi> that he quite forgets the <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits</hi> which ariſe from <hi>reading</hi> the Scriptures, and thoſe many intolerable <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> which flow from the neglect of it; which the ancient Fathers have largely inſiſted upon. <hi>The reading of the Divine Scriptures,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, is a Spiritual Meadow, a Paradiſe of Delights; a better Paradiſe of Delight than that other Paradiſe. God hath planted this Paradiſe not in the Earth, but in the Souls of Believers: He hath placed it not in</hi> Eden <hi>or toward the Eaſt, confining it to one place, but hath extended it to the Ends of the World.—Here is no Serpent, it is a place free from wild Beaſts, and fenced with the Grace of the holy Spirit.—And this Paradiſe hath a Fountain as the other had, a Fountain from which not only four, but myriads of Rivers flow:—Would you know the Nature of it, know it from its uſe. It is not profitable to this preſent Life, but to the Life eternal. Let us ſpend our Time in this Paradiſe, let us ſit by this Fountain, let us abide in the reading of theſe Scriptures. For as thoſe that ſit by a Fountain, and enjoy that cool refreſhing Air, and when the Sun grows hot, dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their Face continually, do drive away the ſtifling Heat, and eaſily cure their troubleſom Thirſt: So he that ſits by the Fountain of the Divine Scriptures, if the flame of Luſt annoy him, bathing his Soul in theſe Waters, he may eaſily extinguiſh it. If fierce Anger moleſt him, inflaming his</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49460:21"/> 
                     <hi>Heart as a boiling Cauldron, by inſtilling a little of this Water, he may preſently repreſs the importunity of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and from all evil Cogitations the reading of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Scriptures delivers the Soul. For which Reaſon the great Prophet</hi> David, <hi>knowing the advantage that comes by reading the Scriptures, compares the Man who conſtantly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to the Scriptures, to a Plant placed by the Rivers of Waters, which always flouriſhes. For as that Tree is not hurt by unſeaſonable Air, or by the ſcorching Rays of the Sun: So that Soul that ſtands by the flowings of the Divine Scriptures, and is continually watered by them, is unconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; if Sickneſs, Loſs, falſe Accuſation, Revilings,—Yea if all the Evils in the World aſſault ſuch a Soul, he eaſily repels all Perturbations of Mind, having ſufficient Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the reading of the Scriptures</hi> 
                     <note n="n" place="margin">De utilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te lectionis Script.</note>. If any Man liſt to ſee more to this purpoſe, let him conſult the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. And as the Benefits are many and ſo great, that a Man may reap from the reading of the Scripture, ſo the ſame St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> tells us, that Myriads of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs ſpring from the neglect of it
<note n="o" place="margin">Proaem. in Epiſt. ad Rom.</note>; many of which he hath given us a particular account of in ſeveral of his Sermons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>Let us now conſider what theſe <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> are the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi> makes ſuch a Noiſe about. Beſides thoſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd by him, he ſays, there are <hi>infinite other</hi> 
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Pag. 52.</note>. Thoſe <hi>infinite other,</hi> I can ſay nothing to, becauſe I know not what they are: If he pleaſe to tell us <hi>ſome</hi> of them (for we cannot expect he ſhould ennumerate <hi>all,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>infinite)</hi> they ſhall be conſidered. All thoſe he is pleaſed to mention are of the ſame kind, <hi>viz.</hi> the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are among Chriſtians from the different Senſes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49460:22"/> they put upon the Scripture, thereby making as many <hi>Bibles</hi> as there are <hi>Men. The unhappy Diviſions,</hi> ſays he, <hi>which are among Chriſtians, ſufficiently inform him, that to ſuch Readers as St.</hi> Peter <hi>calls unwary and ignorant, how ever wiſe they may think themſelves,</hi> Arianiſm <hi>may be as obvious in this Book, as Chriſt's Divinity; and that when ſuch an one undertakes the interpretation of it, 'tis an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard whether at the end, he comes out</hi> Quaker, Anabaptiſt, Presbyterian, Independent, Muggletonian, Socinian <hi>or</hi> Atheiſt: <hi>'Tis a venture whether the Trinity ſhall have place in his Creed or no: Whether he'll allow of Baptiſm or any Sacrament; and whether Cruelty, cutting of Throats, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Tyranny, Dethroning of Kings and Murder of Princes, ſhall not with him become a neceſſary Duty, and a true ſerving of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.
<note n="q" place="margin">Pag. 52.</note>. And in another place, the Reaſon he gives, why the Holy Scriptures are not generally allowed to the Vulgar, is this; <hi>That there may not be as many different Bibles among them, as there are Heads</hi> 
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Pag. 54.</note>: Which is in effect the ſame with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. And in a third; <hi>That it is not only thus in SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERAL PEOPLE, but even the SAME PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON many times hath the faculty of multiplying the Word of God</hi> 
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Chap. 9. pag. 57.</note>. That is, by reading the Scriptures, Men are not only divided one from another, but the ſame Perſon is at different times, divided from himſelf, by putting one Senſe upon them at one time, and another, at another.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall obſerve one thing by the way, before I come to expoſe the Folly of this way of Reaſoning. Had not this Gentleman vainly preſumed, that the Vulgar of our Communion, are as ignorant as thoſe of his own, in other Countries, he would not have laid ſo great ſtreſs upon theſe Words of St. <hi>Peter (the unlearned and unſtable)</hi> and repeated them thrice within the compaſs of one half
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49460:22"/> Sheet, (tho perhaps for a diſguiſe in the words now ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he puts <hi>unwary and ignorant</hi> inſtead of <hi>unlearned and unſtable)</hi> ſince they are ſo far from proving what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that they are a fair Argument for the contrary. For, as I before obſerved, could the <hi>unlearned</hi> have wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the Scriptures, had they not read them? And if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wreſted them, they were to be forbidden to read them, would not the Apoſtle (when the matter requir'd it) have told them ſo, and given this in charge to the Paſtors of the Church? Had he been of the ſame judgment with his Succeſſors at <hi>Rome,</hi> for the laſt three or four hundred years, was it poſſible he ſhould have forgotten this? I appeal to the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: Does he think it was St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s intention that this Epiſtle of his ſhould not be read by thoſe to whom he wrote it? If not, he intended it ſhould be read by the Vulgar, for 'tis certain it was written to ſuch.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall now proceed to the particular conſideration of theſe <hi>Miſchiefs.</hi> Which tho all (as I ſaid before) of the ſame kind; yet becauſe to make the greater ſhew, the Repreſenter hath put them into a different dreſs of words, and diſcourſed of them apart in three ſeveral Chapters <note n="t" place="margin">Chap. 7. 8, 9.</note>, leſt I ſhould be thought to wave any thing material to his purpoſe, I ſhall alſo ſpeak to them ſeverally, and they are theſe:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. <hi>The many Diviſions that are among Chriſtians</hi> 
                        <note n="u" place="margin">Chap. 7. p. 52.</note>.</item>
                     <item>II. <hi>As many different Bibles as there are different Heads</hi> 
                        <note n="w" place="margin">Chap. 8. p. 54.</note>.</item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Not only ſeveral People, but even the ſame Perſon many times has the faculty of multiplying the Word of God</hi> 
                        <note n="x" place="margin">Chap. 9. p. 57. <hi>Miſchief</hi> I.</note>.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>I. Having juſt before ſpoken of the many unhappy Diviſions among Chriſtians, he ſays, <hi>That theſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite other Miſchiefs ariſe from the free permitting the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble among the Multitude</hi> 
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Pag. 52.</note>. Now if he ſpeaks to the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49460:23"/> purpoſe, his meaning muſt of neceſſity be; That <hi>all theſe many unhappy Diviſions</hi> ariſe from this cauſe <hi>only,</hi> or at leaſt from this cauſe <hi>principally.</hi> And therefore no more is here needful than to diſcover the falſeneſs of this Aſſertion. However I ſhall be more liberal, and ſhew theſe two things: 1. That what is here affirm'd is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly falſe. 2. That in caſe it were true, it would not be of force to infer the Concluſion, <hi>viz. That the reading of the Bible ought to be denied to the Vulgar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is notoriouſly falſe, That <hi>all the unhappy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions among Chriſtians take their riſe, either ONLY or CHIEFLY from the free permitting of the Bible among the Multitude.</hi> This will be evident by conſidering theſe five things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That there were <hi>Diviſions</hi> among the <hi>Ancient Guides</hi> or <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That there have been, and ſtill are <hi>Diviſions,</hi> yea as many, among the <hi>Learned</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> as among the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Learned Romaniſts</hi> are divided among themſelves, in all thoſe Points in which they are divided from <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That thoſe very pernicious Doctrines and Practices, which the Repreſenter himſelf mentions, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the <hi>Learned;</hi> and eſpecially from the <hi>Learned</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> And therefore,</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That the <hi>Diviſions</hi> among the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> for the moſt part, are not owing to themſelves, but to the <hi>Learned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. There were <hi>Diviſions</hi> among the ancient <hi>Guides</hi> and <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> and in matters of as great moment, as thoſe are in which the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are divided. As between St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Victor,</hi> St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> and <hi>Stephen,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Theophilus,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49460:23"/> and <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> the Biſhops of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and thoſe alſo of <hi>Sardica, &amp;c.</hi> I wiſh thoſe Diviſions, and many other among the ancient Biſhops were not too well known to need any Proof. Now can the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſay, That theſe Diviſions ſprang from permitting the Bible to the Multitude? I trow not.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There have been, and ſtill are Diviſions, yea as many, among the <hi>Learned</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Almoſt every <hi>Schoolman</hi> is the Head of a <hi>Sect;</hi> and the Controverſies between the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> and the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> are not ſo many, as between the <hi>Thomiſts</hi> and the <hi>Scotiſts.</hi> The Diſſentions between the Regular and Secular Prieſts, have laſted already for ſome Ages, and are likely ſtill to continue; ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Orders, ſo many <hi>Sects</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> you may find among the Regulars; and the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrants,</hi> will as ſoon unite, as the <hi>Dominicans</hi> with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> or the <hi>Franciſcans.</hi> Yea the <hi>Popes themſelves</hi> (the Centre of their Unity) are often divided among themſelves, and their Definitions plainly contradictory one to another. Witneſs Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> I, and Pope <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> III. The former condem'd the Title of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop,</hi> as abominable and Antichriſtian <note n="z" place="margin">Lib. 4. Epiſt. 32, 33, 36, 38.</note>, the later ambitiouſly affected and obtain'd it from the Tyrant <hi>Phocas</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Plat. in vit. Bonifacii III. Sabellic. Ennead. 8. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note>. Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> I. held the Euchariſt was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Infants
<note n="b" place="margin">Aug. Contr. duas Epiſt. Pelag. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. Binii Concil. Tom. 1. p. 769.</note>. Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV. denounced an Anathema againſt thoſe that held it <note n="c" place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 21. Can. 4.</note>. And certainly neither do theſe Diviſions take their Riſe from the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bible by the common People.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Learned Romaniſts</hi> are divided among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in all thoſe Points of Doctrine, in which they are divided from <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> I ſhall inſtance in ſome, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Popes</hi> Infallibility and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Paſtorſhip; his Power over Princes, and Dominion in Temporals; the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49460:24"/> Canon of Scripture, and Traditions of the <hi>Church;</hi> the Sacrifice of the Maſs, and Communion in one kind; the Worſhip of Images, and Invocation of Saints; the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Purgatory and Indulgences; to which I ſhall add but one more, <hi>viz. Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> Tho they ſeem pretty well agreed to burn or hang thoſe that deny it, yet there is not one queſtion about it, in which they are at an agreement among themſelves. To borrow the Words of a learned Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Ireland. No ſooner,</hi> ſays he, <hi>was this fatal Sentence given</hi> (he means the Definition of Tranſubſtantiation in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council) <hi>but as if Pandora</hi>'s <hi>Box had been newly ſet wide open, whole ſwarms of noiſom Queſtions and Debates did fill the Schools. Then it began to be diſputed by what means this Change comes; whether by the Benediction of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or by the repetition of thoſe Words of Chriſt, THIS IS MY BODY? Then was the Queſtion ſtarted, what the demonſtrative Pronoun HOC ſignifies in theſe Words, THIS IS MY BODY? Whether this thing, or this Subſtance, or this Bread, or this Body, or this Meat, or theſe Accidents, or that which is contain'd under theſe Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or this Individuum vagum, or laſtly (which ſeems ſtranger than all the reſt) this nothing?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then it began to be argued, whether the Elements were annihilated? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Matter and Form of them being deſtroyed, their Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence did yet remain? Or the Eſſence being converted, the Exiſtence remain'd?—Then the Schoolmen began to wrangle, what manner of Change this was? Whether a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Change, or a formal Change, or a Change of the whole Subſtance both Matter and Form? And if it were a Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the whole Subſtance; then whether it was by way of Production or by Adduction?</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bp.</hi> Bramh. <hi>Anſw. to the Epiſt. of M.</hi> de la Militiere.</note>. This is only a ſhort taſte of what the Reader may find in the Book quoted in the Margin.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49460:24"/>
                  <p> Nor do they only quarrel about the Manner, but ſome of their greateſt Men do not believe, and others plainly deny the Article it ſelf; as any one may ſee, who will but take the pains to conſult the learned Preface to a Diſcourſe of the Holy Euchariſt, in the two great Points, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and a Treatiſe written by an Author of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> touching <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</hi> It is probable, that if all the Diſputes, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Points controverted among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> were put together, they would not amount to a greater number than thoſe of the Papiſts, in this one Article.</p>
                  <p>To conclude this: Let any <hi>Learned Romaniſt</hi> tell me, what his Judgment is, in any one Point controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted between them and us, and I will engage, upon ſhort warning, to produce another <hi>Learned Romaniſt,</hi> who ſhall contradict him. And, are not Men ſo entirely uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Judgment among themſelves, excellently quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to upbraid Proteſtants with their Diviſions!</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In that he ſays, <hi>To ſuch Readers as St.</hi> Peter <hi>calls <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwary and Ignorant, Arianiſm may be as obvious in this Book as Chriſt's Divinity:</hi> It is a ſign that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected no other than ſuch <hi>unwary and ignorant Readers.</hi> For he muſt be ignorant indeed in theſe Matters, who does not know, That not the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> but the <hi>Learned;</hi> not the Laity, but the Clergy, were the Perſons to whom <hi>Arianiſm</hi> was in this Book ſo obvious; Witneſs the Councils of <hi>Sirmium,</hi> of <hi>Milan</hi> and <hi>Ariminum.</hi> I need not tell him, That one or two of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> either groſly diſſembled, or <hi>Arianiſm</hi> was for a time, more obvious to them in this Book, than <hi>Chriſt's Divinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whereas he ſays, That <hi>when ſuch an one (viz.</hi> one that is Unwary and Ignorant) <hi>undertakes the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting of this Book, 'tis a hazard, whether in the end he comes</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49460:25"/> 
                     <hi>out Quaker, Anabaptiſt, Presbyterian, Independent, Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gletonian, Socinian, or Atheiſt.</hi> He had ſpoken nearer the Truth, if he had ſaid, When ſuch an one takes this Book as interpreted to him by a Popiſh Prieſt or Jeſuit, in the diſguiſe of a Quaker, Anabaptiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We know who have been imploy'd to ſow and foment Diviſions among us, to draw our People into ſeparated Meetings, upon the pretence of a more pure and ſpiritual way of Worſhip. We can tell him of great numbers inſtructed in Handy-craft Trades, trained up to diſpute, one for Presbytery, another for Independency, a third for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſm, ſent over hither by order from <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that when the deluded People have thought they had heard a <hi>gifted Tradeſman,</hi> they have heard a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt in that diſguiſe. We can acquaint him with thoſe who have been detected exerciſing their Talents, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts of Meetings.</p>
                  <p>But that which follows is moſt ſurpriſing: That <hi>it is a venture, whether Cruelty, cutting of Throats, Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Tyranny, dethroning of Kings, murder of Princes, ſhall not with him (viz.</hi> the ignorant Reader) <hi>become a neceſſary Duty, and a true ſerving of the Lord.</hi> This, I ſay, is moſt ſurpriſing; and doubtleſs, he rubb'd his forehead hard, before he wrote it, ſince he knows, That all theſe have, for ſome hundreds of Years, been taught and practiſed by the greateſt Men of his own Church; and therefore it is not a <hi>venture,</hi> but beyond all <hi>perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture,</hi> that when Place and Time ſerve, they will be ſo again. He well knows what the great Cardinals, <hi>Bellarmine, Baronius, Perron,</hi> &amp;c. What the Learned Jeſuits, <hi>Suarez, Leſſius, Azorius,</hi> &amp;c. What his own Country-men, Cardinal <hi>Allen,</hi> Father <hi>Parſons, Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> &amp;c. have written for the <hi>depoſing</hi> and <hi>murdering of Kings.</hi> He knows what Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> VII, <hi>Gregory</hi> IX,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49460:25"/> 
                     <hi>Innocent</hi> III, <hi>Innocent</hi> IV, <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII, <hi>Paul</hi> III, <hi>Pius</hi> V, <hi>Sixtus</hi> V, <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII, have not only taught, but acted in purſuance of theſe Doctrines. He knows there was a <hi>Holy League</hi> among thoſe who had not the <hi>Bible in their Banners,</hi> as well as a <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> among thoſe who had. And he knows, or (at leaſt) may ſoon know, if he pleaſe, That the chief Weapons of the Rebellion in Forty two, were ſetch'd from <hi>Rome;</hi> I mean, the Arguments by which the People were ſtirred up to rebel, were tranſcribed from Popiſh Writers, particularly from <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>Parſons,</hi> out of whom he may ſee in ſome Books then publiſhed, whole leaves together tranſlated. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Diviſions among the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> are very rarely in compariſon owing to themſelves; they are not to be imputed to the different Senſes, which they themſelves in their private reading put upon the Bible, but (for the moſt part) to the different Senſes they receive of it from their Teachers. For the truth of which, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to Hiſtory, and to the common Obſervation of Mankind. If the Repreſenter be not ſatisfied with this, I deſire him to anſwer but this one Queſtion: Whence came it to paſs, that ſo many of the Vulgar in <hi>England, France, Germany,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> &amp;c. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided themſelves from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> before they had the Bible in a Language they underſtood? That Diviſion could not proceed from their reading of the Bible, which was made before they had ever read it. I cannot imagine what Anſwer he can give, but that they followed their Leaders, <hi>Wickliff, Luther, Zuinglius,</hi> &amp;c. who firſt dividing from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> drew the People after them. The Diviſion therefore took its Riſe from the <hi>Learned,</hi> and from them deſcended to the <hi>Ignorant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49460:26"/>
                  <p> The <hi>Trent</hi> Fathers therefore were miſerably miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, in denying the Bible to the Laity only; they ſhould have decreed in the firſt place, that no Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould be ſuffer'd to read it, (that there might be like People, like Prieſt). And this the more prudent Biſhops at <hi>Bononia</hi> were aware of, when they adviſed <hi>Julius</hi> III, <hi>not to permit any Mortal to read more of the Goſpel, than that little which is contained in the Maſs</hi> 
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">Conſil. de Rom. Eccleſ. ſtabiliend. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Vergeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Tom. 1.</note>. I need ſay no more to expoſe the Falſhood of this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, <hi>That</hi> the Diviſions among Chriſtians, proceed <hi>ſolely</hi> or <hi>chiefly</hi> from permitting the Bible among the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> But,</p>
                  <p>2. If this were true, yet it would not be a ſufficient Reaſon for denying the reading of the Bible to the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. For if it were ſo now, it would have been ſo heretofore; it would have been ſo in the early Ages of the Chriſtian Church, when there were as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sects and Hereſies as there are now: It would have been ſo in the Time of the Apoſtles, for in almoſt every Church planted by them, Diviſions preſently ſprang up: It would have been ſo in the Jewiſh Church, for they had their Sects as well as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; yea, it would have been ſo from the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, when the Scripture was firſt publiſh'd.</p>
                  <p>But when the Bible was firſt written, had this been a ſufficient Reaſon, would God have cauſed it to be written in the Vulgar Language of that People to whom it was given, and laid his Command upon <hi>all</hi> without diſtinction, to apply themſelves to the ſtudy of it. And in the ſucceeding Ages of the Jewiſh Church, yea after the Babylonian Captivity (tho ſome new Sects then ſprang up among them) ſo far was it from being thought a Reaſon, why they ſhould not read the Law, that by the Laws of that Nation, every Man was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49460:26"/> to write a Copy of the Law for himſelf, with his own hand. And if the Caſe had been alter'd in the days of our Saviour, would he not have told us? Would he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have reproved the <hi>prying Multitude,</hi> (as the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter is pleaſed to complement the People) for reading the Law and the Prophets? Nay, would he have put them upon the reading of them, as he plainly does, as oft as in his Diſcourſes to the People, he quotes them for the proof of what he ſays. And had his Apoſtles after him thought this a fit Expedient, either for the Prevention or Cure of Diviſions, when they wrote their Epiſtles to thoſe Churches in which Diviſions were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſown, (as the Churches of <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Coloſſe)</hi> would they have addreſſed them to <hi>all</hi> without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and exhorted <hi>all,</hi> that <hi>the Word of God dwell in them richly?</hi> And when, in ſucceeding Ages, the Church was miſerably rent with Schiſms, do any of the Fathers preſcribe this Remedy? Nay, tho St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> &amp;c. ſadly complain of the <hi>abuſe</hi> of Scripture by Hereticks, yet do they not exhort all ſorts of Perſons to read it? In a word, The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, did not think this a fit Expedient, till it was ſo changed from what it was in the beginning, that if St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould have been raiſed again from the Dead, they would not have owned it for that Church which they at firſt planted. I have, I think, ſaid more than enough, to the firſt Miſchief.</p>
                  <p>II. The ſecond (which he gives as the main Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Miſchief</hi> II.</note> why the <hi>Holy Scripture is not allow'd to the Vulgar of his Church without exception)</hi> is this: That if this be allow'd, <hi>there will be as many different Bibles among them, as there are Heads</hi> 
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">Chap. 8. p. 54.</note>: that is, The words of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will be underſtood by them, in as many different ſenſes as there are Men: For he thus explains himſelf;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49460:27"/> 
                     <hi>Tho the Book of the Scriptures does certainly contain the Word of God, yet to every Chriſtian that reads it, 'tis the</hi> Senſe <hi>and</hi> Meaning, <hi>and not the</hi> Letter, <hi>is more properly the Word of God. Now do You but reflect in how many different Senſes the Letter of the Bible is underſtood, and ſo many different Bibles will you find multiply'd by your Followers: And tell me, upon examination, whether this be much fewer than Heads</hi> 
                     <note n="g" place="margin">P. 54.</note>? So wonderfully pleaſed is he with this Conceit, that he preſently falls into a fit of Raillery. <hi>Don't you think there would be a pretty variety of Bibles? there would be this Man's Bible, and that Man's Bible; ſuch an one's Bible, and ſuch an one's Bible; infinite number of Bibles.</hi> But I fear I ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoil his mirth.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not inſiſt upon it; That every <hi>difference in ſenſe,</hi> makes not a <hi>difference of Bibles,</hi> as long as there is an agreement in all things material, in thoſe Points, which by all the differing Parties are acknowledged ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to Salvation. I need not beg this, becauſe they themſelves are forc'd to aſſert it in their own defence: For they acknowledg, that the Vulgar Latin Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bible, differs in many places from the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; That before Pope <hi>Clement</hi>'s Edition, there were many various Readings: That the Bibles ſet forth by <hi>Sixtus</hi> and <hi>Clement,</hi> are different each from other in many Places; and yet they ſay, they are not to be reckoned different Bibles, becauſe they do not differ in any thing material to the Faith.</p>
                  <p>This being premiſed, I return to his Argument, which in ſhort is this: <hi>If the Holy Scriptures ſhould be</hi> generally <hi>allow'd to the Vulgar,</hi> without exception, <hi>they will every one underſtand them in a different ſenſe</hi> 
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Ibid.</note>. Therefore they ought not to be thus allow'd.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49460:27"/>
                  <p> Now in that he ſays <hi>generally,</hi> and <hi>without exception,</hi> He ſuppoſes, That if they be allow'd to the Vulgar, not <hi>generally,</hi> but <hi>with an Exception,</hi> they to whom they are ſo allow'd, will not make them ſo many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Bibles: From whence it plainly follows; That if they ſhould be allow'd to <hi>all, without exception,</hi> yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of that <hi>all,</hi> will underſtand them in the ſame ſenſe; which overthrows his <hi>univerſal</hi> Concluſion, <hi>viz. That there will be as many different Bibles as Heads.</hi> But I paſs this; Nor ſhall I ſtay to ſhew; Firſt, That the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent is notoriouſly untrue. Secondly, That if it were true, yet the ſame Miſchief will follow, if the Vulgar be taught the Bible by their Paſtors, (as he ſays they are in the Church of <hi>Rome)</hi> becauſe they may put as many different Interpretations upon their words, as upon the words of the Bible. But ſhall content my ſelf to return theſe three things in anſwer to the Argument, which will ſufficiently expoſe its abſurdity.</p>
                  <p>Firſt; That it is of equal force againſt the reading of the Bible by the <hi>Learned,</hi> yea, of much greater. The Reaſon is plain, becauſe the <hi>Learned</hi> are thoſe eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who expound the Bible to different Senſes. The moſt zealous <hi>Papiſt,</hi> if he pleaſe to follow the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Direction, ſhall find this as evident as Demonſtration.</hi> Let him firſt ask twenty Lay-men, what is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch a Text, and write down each Man's ſenſe <hi>at length as he delivers it,</hi> in one Column; Then let him conſult twenty of the moſt learned <hi>Popiſh</hi> Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, upon the ſame Text, and write down what each of them ſays in another; then let him compare all the Lay-men ſenſes together, and obſerve all the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences that are between them: Let him then compare all the Learned Commentators ſenſes together, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve likewiſe all the Differences between them; then
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49460:28"/> let him compare the Differences between the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> with thoſe between the <hi>Learned,</hi> and if he find not the former fewer and leſs material than the later, I ſhall own that I am miſtaken.</p>
                  <p>I add; That if the Underſtanding ſome places of Scripture in a different ſenſe, makes different Bibles, then St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> yea, all the Learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Primitive Church, had different Bibles; and therefore (if this Argument ſignify any thing) ought not to have been ſuffered to read the Scripture. The abſurdity of which will yet be more manifeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Where the Vulgar are not permitted to read the Bible, there are as many <hi>different Bibles</hi> (in the Repreſenter's ſenſe) as where they are: Even in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> there are as many, I may truly ſay, many more than among the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> The <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> have one Bible, the <hi>Scotiſts</hi> another; the <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> one, the <hi>Dominicans</hi> another; the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> one, the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> another: The <hi>Scotiſts</hi> Bible teaches, that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Sin, is nothing but the Privation of Original Righteouſneſs; the <hi>Thomiſts</hi> Bible teaches, it is more: The <hi>Franciſcans</hi> find in their Bible the immaculate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Bleſſed Virgin; the <hi>Dominicans</hi> find no ſuch Matter in theirs: The <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> Bible gives to God alone the praiſe of Converting Grace; the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Bible gives it to God, and themſelves too. In many of their Bibles, Tranſubſtantiation is as legible, as theſe words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> in many others, no ſuch Doctrine appears.</p>
                  <p>Yea, the very Popes themſelves (in ſpite of their Infallibility) have Bibles not only <hi>different,</hi> but plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>contradictory.</hi> Pope <hi>Gregory</hi>'s I. Bible, taught him,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49460:28"/> that the Emperor was his Lord; Pope <hi>Gregory</hi>'s VII. that the Emperor was his Vaſſal. Yea, ſome of their Bibles have taught them to be downright Hereticks; ſo did Pope <hi>Honorius</hi>'s, and <hi>John</hi>'s XXIII. And which is yet worſe, not only their Popes, but their Councils too, have had <hi>different Bibles,</hi> as might be ſhew'd at large, if it were needful. Yea if that be true which a great Cardinal has affirmed; That the Precepts of Chriſt may be changed by the Church, and at one time be interpreted to this ſenſe, and at another time to that <note n="i" place="margin">Card. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan. Epiſt. 2. de uſu Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munionis ad Bohem.</note>. Then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may, every Age or every year, have a different Bible.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> grants, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have all the ſame Bible in their <hi>hands,</hi> tho it be <hi>different</hi> in their <hi>Heads;</hi> Thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have in their <hi>Hands</hi> in one Age one Bible; in another Age, another. In this and the Age next foregoing, the Books of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> have been part of the Bible in their Hands, which certainly were not ſo in the Age of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great
<note n="k" place="margin">Greg. Moral. Expoſ. in Job. l. 19. c. 17.</note>.</p>
                  <p>I further add, That their agreement about the ſenſe of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> is as little, as about the ſenſe of the Scripture. <hi>Soto</hi>'s Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and <hi>Catharinus</hi>'s Council of <hi>Trent; Bellarmin</hi>'s Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> are ſo far from being the <hi>ſame,</hi> that they are in many things directly <hi>oppoſite.</hi> And therefore,</p>
                  <p>3. To retort the Argument; <hi>How ſhamefully does the Repreſenter delude the poor Vulgar, in perſwading them, that tho they do not read the Bible, yet the very ſame Word of God is delivered to them by their Teachers; whereas when it comes to be examined, it is not the Word of God, but their Teachers Imaginations they are guided by. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of this by his own experiment. Let him take all</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:49460:29"/> 
                     <hi>the different ſenſes their Teachers put upon the Scripture, and carry them to any Licenſer of his own Church in order to be printed and publiſhed</hi> as the Word of God, <hi>and</hi> Rule of Faith, <hi>and ſee if he can find any who will ſet them forward with an Imprimatur. What an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Impoſture is it then, to let ſo many poor Souls go on with a ſecure confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of following the Word of God, when what they follow is nothing better than the Imaginations and Dreams of their Prieſts!</hi> Let now the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> judg, to whoſe <hi>ſhame</hi> the <hi>Droll is expoſed,</hi> and if he pleaſe, let him ſtill go on to upbraid the Proteſtants with their different Bibles.</p>
                  <p>III. But the <hi>Repreſenter will go farther with us.</hi> For <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Miſchief</hi> III.</note> 
                     <hi>'tis not only thus,</hi> ſays he, <hi>in</hi> ſeveral People, <hi>but even the</hi> ſame Perſon <hi>many times has the faculty of multiplying the Word of God. For how many are there to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Vulgar, who according to their different humours, as their Intereſt changes, according to the different Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions they receive from Confidents, eſpecially ſuch as have gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their good Opinion, eſpouſe different Doctrines and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, and run thorough as many Sects, as there are Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in the Nation? And yet in all their windings, they follow (as they imagine) the Scripture.—Don't you ſee how to theſe</hi> ſame Perſons <hi>the Word of God is not always the</hi> ſame? <hi>It alters according to Seaſons and Times, and it was one Word of God directed them the laſt year, another this,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now ſuppoſe all this to be true of many of the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,</hi> is it not alſo as true of many of the <hi>Learned?</hi> yea of many of the <hi>moſt Learned</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> May it not as truly be ſaid, how many may be found among your <hi>Biſhops, Cardinals</hi> and <hi>Popes,</hi> who according to their different humours, as their Intereſt changes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe different Doctrines and Perſwaſions? Witneſs in elder times Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> and <hi>Vigilius,</hi> who were either
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49460:29"/> Hereticks or Catholicks, as their Intereſt changed. And for later times, witneſs the Cardinal of <hi>Cuſa;</hi> who, one while more zealous than he, for the Authority of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council above the Pope? But when he expected to be made a Cardinal, who more zealous for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Doctrine? Upon which <hi>Richerius</hi> his Words are obſervable: <hi>By this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we are given to know, that very many who have defended the Truth in a ſtate of Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, have deſerted the ſame out of hope of Dignities, and a more plentiful Fortune; and eſpecially out of an ambition of being made Cardinals</hi>
                     <note n="(l)" place="margin">Hiſt. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. general. l. 3. p. 479.</note>. Witneſs <hi>Aeneas Sylvius,</hi> who vehemently oppoſed that Doctrine, when he was Pope, which he had before as vehemently maintained, when he was Clerk to the Council of <hi>Baſil.</hi> And that it was intereſt that gave him this new Light, not I, but <hi>Richerius</hi> and <hi>Maimbourg</hi> plainly aſſert <note n="(m)" place="margin">Richer. Hiſt. Concil. general. l. 4. parte. 1. c. 6. Maimb. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog. <hi>Of the Church of Rome.</hi> c. 25. p. 338.</note>. Yea the Pope himſelf in his Bull of Retractation, ſays in effect as much; for ſpeaking of the Diſputes between him and <hi>Juliano</hi> Cardinal of St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> he confeſſes the Doctrine he forſook was the ancient, and that he embraced was new <note n="(n)" place="margin">Tueba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur antiquam ſententiam, ille novam defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat.</note>. Witneſs the <hi>Cardinal</hi> of <hi>Lorrain:</hi> Does not he he himſelf confeſs, that his <hi>Intereſt</hi> being turn'd, he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it
<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt. of the Counc. of Trent.</hi> l. 8. p. 767.</note>? Was not his Perſwaſion different, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the different <hi>Impreſſions he received</hi> from the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>France?</hi> When he firſt came to <hi>Trent,</hi> how contrary his Sentiments in ſeveral Points were to thoſe he had afterward, when the State of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in <hi>France</hi> was altered, and he had been careſſed by the <hi>Pope,</hi> and his <hi>Holineſs</hi> had <hi>gain'd his good Opinion,</hi> may ſufficiently appear by comparing the places quoted in the Margin <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt. of the Counc. of Trent.</hi> ps. 659, 692, 703, 704, 712, 733, 743, 744, 767, 782, 813.</note>.</p>
                  <p>It's too well known to need to be mentioned, how that <hi>Gardiner, Bonner,</hi> and all the Popiſh Biſhops <hi>(Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher</hi> only excepted) eſpouſed different Doctrines and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49460:30"/> Perſwaſions, as their <hi>Intereſts changed,</hi> and according to the <hi>different Impreſſions they</hi> received, either from the <hi>King</hi> or the <hi>Pope.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>don't you now ſee, how to theſe</hi> ſame <hi>Biſhops, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals and Popes the Word of God was not always the</hi> ſame, <hi>but alter'd according to Seaſons and Times?</hi> That it was one Word of God that directed <hi>Aeneas Sylvius,</hi> while he was Secretary to the Council of <hi>Baſil,</hi> another, while he was Pope. That in King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII's. and King <hi>Edward</hi> VI's. Reigns, the King's Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, was in <hi>Gardiner</hi>'s and <hi>Bonner</hi>'s Bibles: in Queen <hi>Marie</hi>'s Reign, the Pope's was found inſtead of the King's. The Concluſion hence is unavoidable; That if all Men are to be denied the reading of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who <hi>according to their different Humours, as their Intereſt changes, eſpouſe different Doctrines and Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> they muſt be denied to many more than the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, unleſs their Biſhops, Cardinals and Popes are to be placed in that rank.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>In the next place the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> gives us his Reaſons, why the <hi>Vulgar</hi> ſo differ in the ſenſe of the Bible which are two; one of them imply'd, the other expreſſed. That which is imply'd is the <hi>Obſcurity</hi> of the Scripture; That which is expreſs'd is, <hi>the ſetting up every Man's private Reaſon to be Judg of Scripture</hi>
                     <note n="(q)" place="margin">Chap. 9. <hi>p.</hi> 58. <hi>Reaſon</hi> I.</note>.</p>
                  <p>I. The Obſcurity of the Scripture. <hi>For if it be ſo plain and eaſy,</hi> ſays he, <hi>how comes it there is ſo little agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the underſtanding it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When the Proteſtants affirm, that the Scripture is plain and eaſie, they mean it is ſo to thoſe only who read it with honeſt Hearts, who ſincerely deſire to know
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49460:30"/> the Truth, and to direct their Lives anſwerable to it; and they mean, that it's ſo, not ſimply in all things, but in all things neceſſary to Salvation. And when they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this, they affirm no more than St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>whatſoever is in thoſe Scriptures,</hi> (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Scriptures of the old Teſtament, which are more obſcure than thoſe of the new) <hi>it is high and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, they contain nothing but what is true, and that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which is moſt fit for the repairing and reſtoring of Souls, and ſo diſpoſed, that there is no Man, but may draw thence that which is ſufficient for him, provided he comes devoutly and piouſly affected, as true Religion requires</hi> 
                     <note n="(r)" place="margin">Quicquid eſt, mihi crede, in Scripturis illis, altum &amp; divinum eſt: ineſt omnino veritas, &amp; reficiendis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaurandiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> animis accommodatiſſima diſciplina: &amp; plane ita modificata, ut nemo inde haurire non poſſit, quod ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi ſatis eſt, ſi modo ad hauriendum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votè ac piè, ut vera Religio poſcit, accedat. De utilitate credendi. c. 6.</note>. They affirm no more than what St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> did; for he ſays, That <hi>all things neceſſary are manifeſt</hi>
                     <note n="(s)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Hom. 3. in 2. ad Theſſ.</note>. They affirm no more than what the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> did formerly. For <hi>the Holy Scripture,</hi> ſaith Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> (as I find him quoted by the Authors of the Preface of the Mons Teſtament) <hi>is as a great River, which runs always, and which will run to the end of the World. The little Children and the Men of full Stature, the ſtrong and the weak, do there find that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Water that ſprings up even to Heaven. It offers it ſelf to all, and it ſuits it ſelf to all. It hath a ſimplicity that abaſes it ſelf to the moſt ſimple Souls, and a height that exerciſes and raiſes the moſt lofty</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="margin">P. 9.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Nay they ſay no more than what many learned <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> of this preſent Age have ſaid. The Biſhop of <hi>Vence,</hi> ſpeaking of the new Teſtament, ſays, <hi>The Son of God hath in it taken care to teach us CLEARLY and DISTINCTLY, our whole Duty to him, as well as our whole Duty to our. Neighbour and our ſelves. This is</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:49460:31"/> 
                     <hi>that which the Goſpels contain; The Epiſtles of the Apoſtles are a Comment upon it, and an Explication more enlarged and diſtinct, which leave not any thing in the Chriſtian Life we ought to live upon Earth, unexplain'd</hi> 
                     <note n="(t)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Preface of Mr.</hi> Arnaud.</note>. And Mr. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naud</hi> ſays, <hi>That the holy Fathers have noted, that one of thoſe things which ſhew the Divinity of the holy Scriptures, and in which they excel all the Writings of Men, is this, That they are equally accommodated to the Learned and the Ignorant, to little Children and to grown Men, to the weak and to the perfect, to the ſhallow and the more profound Wits</hi> 
                     <note n="(u)" place="margin">De la Lect de l'Ecri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſainte l. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note>.</p>
                  <p>But the Repreſenter asks; <hi>If the Scripture be ſo plain and eaſy, how comes it there is ſo little agreement in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding it? How are there ſo many different and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Diviſions, Sects and Perſwaſions in this one Nation? How comes it, that even in the eſſentials of Chriſtianity, concerning the Trinity</hi> &amp;c. <hi>there has been, and at preſent is ſo great diverſity among thoſe that read the Scripture?</hi> I anſwer</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the agreement among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> is not ſo little as he pretends: That the Reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in all eſſential Points of Faith, any Man may be ſatisfied, who will take the pains to read over the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Confeſſions. But,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let the Diſagreement be more or leſs, it proceeds not from the Obſcurity of the Scriptures. This is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe the Diſagreement among thoſe that read the Scripture, is as great in thoſe things that are moſt <hi>plainly,</hi> as in thoſe that are more <hi>obſcurely</hi> delivered. Can anything be more plain, than theſe words of Chriſt concerning the Cup, <hi>Drink ye all of it</hi> 
                     <note n="(w)" place="margin">Mat. 26. 27.</note>? Or thoſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in which he applys this Drinking to the Lay-Corinthians
<note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 25.</note>? Suppoſe it was Chriſt's Intention, that the Laity ſhould partake of the Cup, as well as the Bread; would not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49460:31"/> thoſe Men, who do not ſee it in theſe words, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Words he had expreſs'd it, have found out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning? It's plain then, that it is not the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Text, from whence this diverſity of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation ariſes. But.</p>
                  <p>2. To gratify the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> I'le plainly tell him what it is. 1. In thoſe who have different Luſts and Intereſts to ſerve, 'tis their different Luſts and Intereſts with which the Scriptures muſt be forced to comply. 2. In thoſe who are ſincere, and do not profeſs contrary to their Belief, it is the different Prejudice or Principle they are poſſeſs'd with. Tho the Scripture ſpeaks ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo plainly againſt the Doctrine and Worſhip of ſuch a ſort of Men, yet if it be inconſiſtent with that which they have laid for the main Principle and Foundation of their Faith, they can never perſwade themſelves that the Words are to be taken according to the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and obvious ſenſe, but muſt find out ſome other meaning for them. For inſtance: It is a Principle with the Romaniſts that their Church cannot err: Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Scripture be never ſo expreſs againſt the Worſhip of Images, againſt Tranſubſtantiation, againſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in one kind, againſt the Propitiatory Sacrifice of the Maſs, againſt Prayer in an unknown Tongue, yet they muſt of neceſſity conclude, that it does not mean what it ſeems to ſay, becauſe if it ſhould, it unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly follows, that their Church hath goſly err'd, which according to their Principle is as impoſſible, as that the Truth and Promiſe of God ſhould fail. And that it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this Principle, &amp; not the Obſcurity of the Scripture, that makes the difference in many Texts between them and us, is evident enough by this conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> That they cannot ſee that in the plaineſt words, that is contrary to their Principle; whereas in words not only
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49460:32"/> obſcure, but moſt remote and impertinent, they can ſee that which is agreeable thereto.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They cannot ſee that in the plaineſt words, that is contrary to their Principle. If to worſhip an Image be unlawful, their Church hath err'd; therefore they cannot ſee it is forbid in the Second Commandment; tho it is hard to conceive that other Words can be uſed more full to that purpoſe. For be it <hi>graven Image,</hi> or <hi>graven Thing,</hi> or <hi>Idol</hi> that is forbidden, it matters not; ſince the <hi>Similitude</hi> or Likeneſs of any thing in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is forbidden alſo.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But ſee now, how they can find that in the moſt remote and impertinent Text, that is agreeable to their Principle. Would you have a Scripture for the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> gives you <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 34, 35. <hi>Swear not by the Heaven, for it is God's Throne, nor by the Earth, for it is his Footſtool</hi> 
                     <note n="(y)" place="margin">De Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note>. If you think this not clear enough, take 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. <hi>Thou haſt known the holy Scriptures from a Child</hi>
                     <note n="(z)" place="margin">Ibid.</note>. The Scriptures are called <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> therefore the Images of Chriſt and his Saints are to be worſhip'd. Here's a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration as bright as Midnight. He muſt be ſtark blind, or ſhut his Eyes hard, who can avoid its light. I omit many other Inſtances which are ready at hand. By theſe now mention'd, it's manifeſt enough, that Mens Diſagreement about the Senſe of Scripture, doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from its obſcurity, but from the different Principles or Prejudices they are prepoſſeſt with. Better would it be for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> were it more obſcure in many Points than it is: And were it but as clear for them, as it is againſt them, they would not then complain of its Obſcurity, or prohibit the Vulgar the reading of it.</p>
                  <p>II. But <hi>the Proteſtants are for ſetting up every Man's private Reaſon to be Judg of Scripture.</hi> What? to be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49460:32"/> Judg of what in Scripture ought to be received, and what rejected, as the Socinians do? This is a very diſingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Miſrepreſentation.</hi> Much more remote from Truth is it, That <hi>they are far worſe in this, than the rankest So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian in the World</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">P. 58.</note>. The Proteſtant, he very well knows, being ſatisfied by his Reaſon concerning the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority of the Scripture, he firmly aſſents to whatſoever he finds delivered in it, tho he be not able to conceive how it ſhould be. He indeed uſes his Reaſon in judging of the ſenſe of Scripture, which he muſt of neceſſity do, or elſe he can have no reaſon to believe it in a true, rather than a falſe ſenſe: But having to the beſt of his underſtanding found out the meaning of it, he makes neither <hi>common</hi> nor <hi>private</hi> Reaſon the <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of what is to be received, ſo as to admit nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Faith, but what he is able fully to underſtand. Tho he meets with ſome things which are above his Capacity, yet he does not ſay as <hi>Socinus,</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt's Satisfaction, <hi>If the very word were in Scripture, not once, but often, yet I would not believe it;</hi> but thinks he has the greateſt Reaſon in the World to believe them, becauſe God has deliver'd them. And that ſome things in Scripture are above his Capacity; this he thinks is ſo far from being a diſcouragement, that it is rather a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to his Faith; for he might be tempted to ſuſpect the Divinity of the Scriptures, if he found nothing in them above the reach of his own little Underſtanding, either at firſt to find out, or afterward to comprehend.</p>
                  <p>And if this be to make <hi>private Reaſon,</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of Scripture, we need not be aſhamed to own it. For this is no more than what our Bleſſed Saviour allowed to private Perſons. He frequently appealed to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Old Teſtament, but he left it to every man's Reaſon to judge, whether they were for him or againſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49460:33"/> him. Yea, did he not ſeverely reprove the <hi>promiſcuous Multitude,</hi> for not judging even of themſelves what was right <note n="(b)" place="margin">Luk. 12. 57.</note>? For to the Multitude (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>v.</hi> 54.) theſe words were directed. This is no more than what the Apoſtles of our Lord have laid as a Duty upon pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians; St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands them <hi>to prove all things</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 21.</note>; and thought the common Chriſtians of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> wiſe enough to <hi>judg what he ſaid</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 15.</note>: St. <hi>John</hi> requires them, to <hi>try the Spirits whether they be of God</hi> 
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 1.</note>: And can they do this if they may not judg of the ſenſe of the Scripture? This is no more than what St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> frequently exhorted the People to, and ſharply reproved their neglect of it.</p>
                  <p>Yea, notwithſtanding the loud cry they make againſt <hi>private Reaſon</hi> and the <hi>private Spirit,</hi> the Roman Clergy themſelves are forced to appeal to it. For when to draw Men over from us to them, they produce ſo many Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſo many Reaſons (ſuch as they are) fetch'd from Scripture; Do they not make every Man's Reaſon Judg, whether theſe Scriptures and theſe Reaſons are to the purpoſe?</p>
                  <p>If they ſay, a Man muſt uſe his Reaſon to judg which is the true Church, but having once found it, he muſt then take the ſenſe of Scripture upon the Church's word: nothing can be ſaid more abſurd: Becauſe a Man muſt judg of theſenſe of the Scripture, before he can diſcern which is the true Church; ſince that can no otherwiſe be known than by thoſe Characters the Scripture gives of it. Beſides, one of their own Marks of the true Church, is the <hi>Holineſs of its Doctirne</hi> 
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">Bell. de Notis Eccleſ. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note>: A Man therefore muſt know what the Doctrine of a Church is, before he can know it to be a true Church; and how ſhall a Man know this, but by firſt examining her Doctrine by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? A Man muſt therefore know the ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49460:33"/> before he can know the true Church. But if it ſhould be granted, that when a Man once knows the true Church, he muſt then underſtand the Scripture as the Church does; yet tell me, why he muſt do ſo? Is it becauſe he hath Reaſon, or no Reaſon, ſo to do? You will not ſay, becauſe he hath no Reaſon, (for you your ſelf give Reaſons why he muſt) And if it be becauſe he hath Reaſon, he then makes his Reaſon Judg of the ſenſe of Scripture, as well as the Proteſtant.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> he ſays, <hi>is but one;</hi> that's gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And <hi>all Chriſtians are directed to meet in this ONE Faith, to be of ONE SPIRIT and ONE MIND to ſay all the ſame thing.</hi> This is alſo granted. <hi>Now can you imagine it poſſible,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for all Chriſtians to concur in the ſame Belief, while the Scripture being but ONE which they read, their private Judgments give</hi> differing <hi>and</hi> contrary <hi>Interpretations of it, and carry them ſeveral ways</hi> 
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">Chap. 9. P. 58.</note>? And will it be poſſible for <hi>all Chriſtians to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in the ſame Belief,</hi> if the Scriptures be denied to the Vulgar? For do not the <hi>private Judgments</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> give as <hi>differing</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> Interpretations of it, and carry them as many <hi>ſeveral ways?</hi> And therefore are there not as many <hi>Diviſions</hi> among your ſelves (as has been ſhew'd) as there are among <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> And is it not ridiculous, ſo often to inſiſt upon that as a ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Remedy of Diviſions, which is ſo ineffectual, that the Diſeaſe is as prevalent, where it is uſed, as where it is not?</p>
                  <p>The Repreſenter may perhaps ſay, That their <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> are not in matters of <hi>Faith:</hi> If not, then nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are ours, ſince theirs are in matters as conſiderable as ours are. But the beſt on't is, if notwithſtanding their <hi>Differences</hi> among themſelves, they are ſtill of <hi>one</hi> Faith; then the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> alſo may be of one Faith,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49460:34"/> not only <hi>among themſelves,</hi> but <hi>with them</hi> too, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are no Hereticks; ſince Proteſtants differ no more from them, than many of them do one from another.</p>
                  <p>Tho therefore it be the Duty of Chriſtians to be all of <hi>one Mind,</hi> and to <hi>ſpeak the ſame things;</hi> and tho I ſee no reaſon to queſtion, but God hath afforded ſuch helps in order thereunto, which if they were not wanting to themſelves in the uſe of, they might attain to this <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> Yet we have already ſeen, that the withholding the Scripture from the Vulgar is none of thoſe means; and tho ſome who will be wiſer than God, have thought fit to make trial of it, yet they have hitherto found it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuccesful. And for thoſe means which God hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed, as little Reaſon have we to expect, that they ſhould by all Chriſtians be faithfully uſed and applied, and they thereby be brought to this perfect Unity, as to expect, that all Men ſhould become ſober, and juſt, and charitable, and devout, which God has made no leſs their Duty, and for the effecting of which, he hath vouchſafedas pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful means.</p>
                  <p>But now let us again try, whether this long Harangue be not of equal force, againſt the reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the <hi>Learned,</hi> as by the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>If the different Sects in Religion proceed from the reading of the Scripture by the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> how comes it that there are ſo many <hi>different</hi> and <hi>contrary Diviſions, Sects</hi> and <hi>Perſwaſions</hi> among you <hi>Romaniſts?</hi> How comes it that even in thoſe things, that by the <hi>differing Parties</hi> are reckon'd <hi>Matters of Faith,</hi> there hath been, and at preſent is, ſo great Diverſity? The buſineſs is, you ſuffer every <hi>Learned</hi> Man's <hi>private Reaſon</hi> to be <hi>Judg</hi> of Scripture, which when put to the teſt, proves in thouſands and thouſands to be no better than Paſſion, Prejudice, Intereſt, Imagination, Gueſſing, or Fancy.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49460:34"/> Don't you find by experience, that there's no Propoſal made, but preſently the <hi>Learned</hi> are divided about it? as they were in almoſt every Queſtion in the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> nor could the Controverſies be decided by the Fathers, but they were forc'd to make many of their Decrees in ſuch general Terms (for the gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the contending Parties) as might be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to contrary Senſes? Don't you ſee again, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Scholar's Reaſon is different, as their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, Parts, Education, Temper, Inclinations, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are different? That as every one has a <hi>Head</hi> of his own, ſo he has generally a <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>way of reaſoning</hi> of his own? Nay, are not the <hi>Learned</hi> ſo <hi>inconſtant</hi> even to themſelves too, that what is Reaſon to them at one time, is unreaſonable at another? How then can you permit a thing ſo <hi>ſlippery,</hi> ſo <hi>weak, vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wavering, changeable, inconſtant,</hi> as you ſee the <hi>private Reaſon</hi> of the Learned is, to be rely'd on by them, as their Guide in expounding of Scripture? How can you imagine it poſſible for all Chriſtians to concur in the <hi>ſame Belief,</hi> while the <hi>Learned,</hi> who read and expound the Scripture, give <hi>differing</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of it? For as long as the Scripture is no otherwiſe in their <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Hearts,</hi> than by the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation</hi> they make of it, their <hi>Faith</hi> muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be as <hi>various</hi> as their <hi>Interpretation.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And is not the Story of the <hi>Manna</hi> (which follows) as applicable to the <hi>Learned?</hi>
                     <q>For, was not the taſte of the <hi>Manna</hi> as different to the Prieſts, as it was to the People? Did it not reliſh according to that kind of Meat, that was moſt grateful to every Prieſt's Palate? Now if the Prieſts in <hi>Canaan</hi> had receiv'd a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of bringing forth that ſort of Meat, whoſe taſte ſhould be like that of the <hi>Manna</hi> they ate in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49460:35"/> was it poſſible they ſhould all agree in their Diſh? Since tho the <hi>Manna</hi> was the ſame they all fed on, yet the Reliſh was as different as their Tempers and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats. Don't you therefore ſee, that Men will never be of <hi>one Spirit,</hi> and <hi>one Mind,</hi> until the reading of the Scripture be prohibited to the <hi>Learned?</hi> and not to <hi>ſome,</hi> but to <hi>all,</hi> his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> as <hi>Infallible,</hi> only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted? For if it be allow'd to the <hi>Cardinals</hi> (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Eminences above others) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> they will never agree in the ſenſe of it: For I can tell you of many <hi>Cardinals</hi> who have differ'd from his Holineſs, and among themſelves too, about the ſenſe of it. Is it not then as <hi>plain as Demonſtration,</hi> that there will be no end of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, as long as the Scriptures are read, by any Man in the World, beſides the Pope? And perhaps not then neither, for ſince he is not <hi>infallible</hi> but when he ſpeaks from his <hi>Chair,</hi> (which ſeldom happens) at other times he may chance to contradict himſelf, and give one ſenſe of Scripture this Year, another the next. It were therefore moſt adviſable (could it poſſibly be effected) that the Book it ſelf were utterly aboliſhed.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let not any Man interpret this to the diſparagement of Learning, ſince nothing can be more evident, than that the Learned have vaſt Advantages above the reſt of Mankind, for attaining to the true meaning of the more obſcure Texts of Scripture; provided they ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely ſearch after Truth, and are ſo humble, ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their own liableneſs to miſtake, that they daily implore the Divine Aſſiſtance: But if they be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of theſe Qualifications, they are not only as ſubject to err, but to err more dangerouſly than others.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the <hi>10th</hi> Chapter, the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> talks again at the ſame impertinent rate; ſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49460:35"/> to him is this way of reaſoning, that he naturally falls into it, in every Chapter. But the Vanity of it lies ſo open, that it need not be further expoſed. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man pleaſe to conſult the place, I ſhall leave it to himſelf to judg, whether it be not every whit as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable againſt permitting the Scripture to the Learned as the Vulgar.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> may ſay, The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does not allow the Learned to interpret Scripture ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own private Reaſon: For the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> has decreed, That no Man preſume to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scripture, <hi>contrary to the ſenſe of the Church, or the unanimous conſent of the Fathers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And has not the Church of <hi>England,</hi> her <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> contrary to which ſhe allows none of her Members to interpret Scripture? Does ſhe not admit all ſuch Traditional Interpretations as can be derived from the Fountain? And for all ſuch Texts as are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and doubtful, does ſhe not direct the Vulgar to conſult their Guides? Tho it is true, ſhe does not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to believe, that <hi>White</hi> is <hi>Black,</hi> or that <hi>Vice</hi> is <hi>Vertue,</hi> if the Prieſt ſays that it is. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> denies them the liberty of interpreting the Scripture in their own ſenſe; it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that they commonly take it; elſe how comes it, that they give ſuch <hi>different ſenſes</hi> of the <hi>ſame Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> How comes it, that many of the Learned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the ſixth Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> of the ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal eating of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Fleſh; and many as learned as they, ſay, that no ſuch matter is there intended? How comes it, when ſo many tell us, that theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> are ſo plain for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> that he muſt be quite blind who does not ſee it? that others, whoſe ſight is as good as theirs, tell us, they are not able to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49460:36"/> ſee this in them? Do theſe Learned Men, in their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Scripture, give us the ſenſe of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, or do they not? If not, they follow their own <hi>private Reaſon;</hi> if they do, their Church gives contrary ſenſes of Scripture, and is as far from being <hi>one</hi> in this reſpect, as it is from being <hi>Catholic.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He confeſſes, <hi>p.</hi> 63. That <hi>ſome of the Proteſtants, to keep up the Face of the Church, do ſpeculatively contend for Authority and Guides:</hi> But then he ſays, <hi>In Fact they defeat all theſe their Pretenſions.</hi> How do they <hi>in Fact</hi> defeat them? Becauſe <hi>they own no Authority ſo great or ſafe, but it is to be ſubjected to the controul of every private Examiner.</hi> They own an Authority ſo great, as to Matters of External Government, as to be ſubject to the controul of no Man, who lives in Communion with the Church. But he means, an Authority ſo great, that whatſoever the Church <hi>commands and preſcribes to be receiv'd, as the Truth and Faith of Chriſt, it ought to be received.</hi> But can the Church have no Authority, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Men are bound to believe, <hi>without examination,</hi> whatſoever ſhe preſcribes to be believed? If ſo, then had ſhe no Authority in our Saviour's and his Apoſtles days; no, nor for ſeveral Ages after them. For if any ſuch Authority had been own'd in the fourth Century, how came it to paſs, that after the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſy ſpread more than it had done before?</p>
                  <p>If this be <hi>to open a Gate to all the Fanaticiſms and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſms</hi> in the World, 'tis certain the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> did not firſt open it, but it was long before open'd by our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> when he gave this Command to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; <hi>Call no Man Father upon the Earth, for one is Your Father which is in Heaven; neither be ye called Maſters, for one is Your Maſter, even Chriſt</hi> 
                     <note n="(h)" place="margin">Mat. 23. 9, 10.</note>. As much as to ſay, There is none upon Earth, by whoſe ſenſe a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49460:36"/> is to be abſolutely determin'd, his Faith is not to be reſolv'd into any Man's Authority.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>by the Creed, all Chriſtians are bound to believe the Holy Catholic Church.</hi> Yes, That there is ſuch a Church, and that this Church teaches all Truths neceſſary to be known: But it is one thing to believe this, another thing to believe as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth. And tho <hi>Proteſtants</hi> never refuſe to yield aſſent to all ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as the Church truly Catholic hath in all Ages taught; yet they can ſee no reaſon to pin their Faith upon the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> there being as vaſt a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> and the <hi>Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> as between the <hi>Church of York</hi> and the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Heb. 13. 17. <hi>commands all to obey, and ſubmit to thoſe that are over them.</hi> 'Tis true, and I grant, that <hi>by thoſe that are over them,</hi> he means Eccleſiaſtical Superiors. But does not the ſame St. <hi>Paul</hi> command Children to obey their Parents, and Servants to obey their Maſters? Would he therefore have all Children and Servants, to take their Faith upon truſt from their Parents and Maſters? He alſo commanded every Soul to be ſubject to the Higher Powers; and yet I am pretty confident, that his meaning was not, that every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould then believe as the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor did.</p>
                  <p>But he commands to <hi>obey</hi> and <hi>ſubmit,</hi> not <hi>only as to External Government, but as to Truth and Belief.</hi> Then thoſe who had <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops (as a great part of the <hi>Church</hi> for ſome time had) were bound to believe, that Chriſt was not God; and thoſe who had <hi>Donatiſt</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, were bound to believe that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> was ſo far from being the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> that it was not ſo much as a Part of it. But how does the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi> prove, That the People ought abſolutely to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49460:37"/> their Faith to thoſe that are over them? becauſe the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>whoſe Faith follow.</hi> And does he not ſay, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>Be ye Followers of them, who through Faith and Patience inherit the Promiſes?</hi> Are we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bound to believe, as every deceaſed Chriſtian hath believed? In both places the Apoſtle ſpeaks of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans departed this Life: in the later of Chriſtians indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently, in the former of Chriſtian Biſhops; And the words ſhould be render'd, <hi>Remember them which have had the Rule over You, which have ſpoken to You the Word of God</hi> (ſuch, for inſtance, as <hi>James</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> who had witneſs'd the Faith by his Death) <hi>whoſe Faith follow.</hi> And the meaning is this; Imitate them in their Conſtancy and Perſeverance in the Chriſtian Profeſſion and Practice, notwithſtanding all the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions you meet with in the World.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 15. may relate either to <hi>Timothy</hi> himſelf, or to that Summary of Chriſtian Doctrine that follows. But ſuppoſe it relate to the Church, that particular Church was primarily meant, in which <hi>Timothy</hi> was directed how to behave himſelf; and I think no <hi>Romaniſt</hi> ſays, That a Man is bound to believe as every particular Church believes.</p>
                  <p>The words of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 17. <hi>(If he hear not the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen Man, and a Publican)</hi> are alſo impertinent, becauſe he ſpeaks there, not of Matters of Faith, but of Fact, and directs what courſe is to be taken for the ending of private Quarrels between Man and Man; tho had he ſpoken of Matters of Faith, they would not have been to the purpoſe; becauſe by the Church, can be meant no other than that particular Church, of which the offending Brother was a Member. I need ſay no more, to ſhew how uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding thoſe Reaſons are, by which he would perſwade
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49460:37"/> us to abandon our Reaſon, and to take the ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon truſt from his Church.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>I Proceed now to the fourth and laſt Head, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>falſe Conſtructions</hi> (as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> calls them) which the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> make of this Practice of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> or the <hi>wrong Inferences</hi> they deduce from it. Which are theſe three;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the Vulgar Papiſts are deprived of the Word of God.</item>
                  <item>2. That they take up all their Belief upon truſt.</item>
                  <item>3. That the Reaſon why they are not permitted to read the Bible, is for fear, leſt they ſhould diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Errors of their Religion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Whether theſe are <hi>Miſconſtructions,</hi> or no, I ſhall leave the impartial Reader to judg, after I ſhall have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd thoſe Reaſons by which he endeavours to prove that they are ſo.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>The firſt Proteſtant Inference is: That the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Papiſts are <hi>deprived of the Word of God, of the Food of their Souls</hi> 
                     <note n="(i)" place="margin">Chap. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 43, 44, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                     </note>To prevent Cavils and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions, I premiſe this: The Proteſtant does not ſay, that the Vulgar Papiſts have nothing of the Scripture allow'd them. He very well knows, that ſome ſhreds of it are now and then given them in Sermons, and ſome ſmall parcels in their Catechiſms, and Manuals of Devotion. But what then? Will it hence follow,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49460:38"/> that it is falſe to ſay, they are deprived of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Will not every Man ſay, That he is deprived of his Father's Will, who is allowed no more than the ſight of here and there a Line tranſcrib'd from it? Or that a Man's Inheritance is detain'd from him, who has no more than a ſmall Penſion given him out of it?</p>
                  <p>One may a little wonder, that this ſhould be reckon'd a <hi>falſe Inference.</hi> What! are they not depriv'd of the <hi>Word of God,</hi> who are not ſuffer'd to <hi>read it,</hi> or ſo much as to <hi>have it</hi> in a Language they underſtand? No, ſays the <hi>Repreſenter; The Vulgar of our Communion have more of this Holy Food, than thoſe of any other Perſwaſion whatſoever<note n="(k)" place="margin">P. 45.</note>.</hi> This is yet more wonderful, That they ſhould not be permitted to <hi>have it;</hi> and yet that they ſhould <hi>have more of it,</hi> than thoſe who have the <hi>whole of it</hi> in their Hands, and daily read it. How ſhall we unriddle this? Why, <hi>They are taught it by their Paſtors.</hi> Be it ſo; Does it thence follow, that they have <hi>more</hi> of it than thoſe of other Perſwaſions, who are taught it by their Paſtors as well as they? For whereas he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſuggeſts, That the Proteſtants are for <hi>leaving their Paſtors, that they may teach themſelves:</hi> that's a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny. Tho the Proteſtants read the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet they do not reject their Paſtors; They do not think, the uſe of the one does render the other needleſs now, any more than it did in the firſt Ages of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, when they both went together, and were both thought neceſſary. But that they who are taught it by their Paſtors <hi>only,</hi> ſhould have <hi>more</hi> of it than thoſe who are both taught it by them, and have the whole of it in their own poſſeſſion, is as true, as that a <hi>part</hi> is more than the <hi>whole.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> will ſay; Their <hi>Paſtors</hi> teach them all that is neceſſary for them to know. How ſhall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49460:38"/> the Vulgar know this? We can tell them of Paſtors who have concealed from their People ſome of the moſt neceſſary Points of the Chriſtian Faith; but I need not name them to the <hi>Repreſenter.</hi> But how are the People aſſur'd, that what they teach them, is indeed the Word of God, and not their own Inventions, when they are not ſuffered to examine it? As it was foretold that <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> ſhould ariſe, ſo every Age ſince hath ſeen that Prediction verified; and for this Reaſon St. <hi>John</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts Vulgar Chriſtians, as well as others, to bring their Teachers Doctrines to the Trial
<note n="(l)" place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 1.</note>. Is it neceſſary that every one that is <hi>commiſſion'd to teach,</hi> ſhould be ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, as to deliver nothing but what he believes to be the Faith of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> The Biſhop of <hi>Minori</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> thought otherwiſe, he was afraid there might be many Prieſts who were real Infidels <note n="(m)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt. of the Counc. of</hi> Trent, l. 2. p. 241.</note>. And if the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> be not ſatisfied with this, we can produce thoſe in this very Age, who have taught that as a neceſſary Article of Faith, which they were ſo far from believing <hi>neceſſary,</hi> that they could not perſwade themſelves it was <hi>true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if the Prieſt be <hi>honeſt,</hi> is he alſo <hi>infallible?</hi> This the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> muſt ſuppoſe, or elſe he reaſons at an abſurd rate: For thus he argues; <hi>Was Mary Magdalen deprived of the Word of God, who placed at her Saviour's Feet, heard it from his own moſt ſacred Mouth? Were thoſe People deprived of the Word of God, to whom the Apoſtles were ſent to preach, for thoſe ſeveral Years, before any of the Goſpel was in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> It is not <hi>writing,</hi> we know, that makes it the <hi>Word of God,</hi> for all that <hi>Word of God</hi> that is now <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> was once <hi>unwritten.</hi> But pray Sir tell me; Is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing taught by a Prieſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as certainly the <hi>Word of God,</hi> as that which was taught by our Bleſſed Saviour, and his Apoſtles? Is every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49460:39"/> Prieſt at length become <hi>Infallible?</hi> If ſo, what a ſhame is it that any Controverſies are left among your ſelves, when every Pariſh affords an <hi>infallible Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of Scripture? If not, then they may teach that for the Word of God, which is nothing leſs. However, all that we contend for, is, That the Vulgar may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to read that Word which <hi>Mary</hi> heard, for that ſhe heard was the ſame that is now written; and had it been then written from Chriſt's Mouth, can any Man be ſo ſenſleſs as to imagine, that after he had done ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he would have forbidden her, under ſevere Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to read it?</p>
                  <p>But let us now ſuppoſe, That every <hi>Roman</hi> Teacher is both <hi>able</hi> and <hi>ſincere;</hi> will it hence follow, that the People may not read the Scriptures? Had St. <hi>Luke</hi> thought ſo, he would never have commended the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> for <hi>ſearching the Scriptures, whether thoſe things that were ſpoken by St.</hi> Paul <hi>were ſo</hi>
                     <note n="(n)" place="margin">Act. 17. 11.</note>. Had St. <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thought ſo, would he have proved what he ſaid by Scripture? (for in doing ſo, he put his Hearers upon the ſearching it) and thereby taught all ſucceeding Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors what they ought to do? To which purpoſe the words of <hi>Origen</hi> are obſervable <note n="(o)" place="margin">In cap. 3. Epiſt. ad Rom.</note>; <hi>If ſuch and ſo great an Apoſtle, did not ſuppoſe his Authority ſufficient Warrant to his Sayings, unleſs he made it appear, that what he ſays is written in the Law and the Prophets, how much more ought we little Ones obſerve this, that we do not bring forth ours, but the Sentences of the Holy Spirit?</hi> Now I preſume it will not be denied, but St. <hi>Paul</hi> was as faithful and able a Teacher as any in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> If it ſhould, yet doubtleſs it will be granted that our Saviour may compare with the beſt of them; and he (as we have heard before) frequently ſent his Hearers to the Scriptures. And if we conſult the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49460:39"/> Fathers, eſpecially St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> (who was as diligent a Paſtor as any the Church can now boaſt of) we ſhall find, that notwithſtanding his abundant pains in teaching, he vehemently exhorted the People to read the Scriptures themſelves, and enforc'd his Exhortation by many powerful Arguments. Omitting many others, I ſhall reciet one Paſſage in his <hi>10th</hi> Homily, on the firſt Chapter of the Goſpel of St. <hi>John; Before I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> (ſaith he to his Hearers) <hi>to explain the words, I will ask one favour of you, which I beſeech you not to deny me, for it is nothing burdenſom, nothing hard to be done, which I ask, and much more profitable to you than to me. What is it then which I deſire? That one Day in the Week, at leaſt on Saturday, you take care to read that part of the Goſpel which I am to explain to you, that every one take it into his Hands, repeat it often at Home, conſider the Scope of it, mark what is clear, and what obſcure, and what ſeems repugnant in it; and weighing all things beforehand, do you thus preſent your ſelves to hear. This will bring no ſmall profit both to you and to me. For it will be no great labour to me, to make you underſtand the force of the Goſpel, when you have before render'd it, as to the words at leaſt, familiar to your ſelves at Home. And you will be not only more quick and ready to hear and learn, but alſo to teach others. There are many here preſent, who hear and endeavour to retain the words, and what I ſay upon them, who would receive no great benefit, tho I ſhould ſpend a whole Year in preaching upon them. Why? Becauſe by the bye, and only for a little time here, they apply their minds to them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I grant, <hi>It was Preaching, Teaching, and Inſtructing by word of Mouth, was the means appointed by Chriſt for planting his Goſpel.</hi> But what then? doth it follow, that when the Goſpel was written, it might not be read
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49460:40"/> by the <hi>Vulgar?</hi> No more doubtleſs, than that it might not be read by the <hi>Learned;</hi> for that was the Means uſed for planting it among both. Nor can we well imagine, how it could at firſt be otherwiſe planted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was then to be confirm'd by Miracles. And ſuppoſe it were true, that <hi>the Apoſtles who were thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to preach, had never any Command to write;</hi> Is not this as good a Reaſon, why the Prieſts may not read the Goſpel, as why the People may not?</p>
                  <p>In the words following, the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſums up his Argument, <hi>viz. Since then the Papiſts are taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Word of God, the very ſame way that Chriſt himſelf taught all thoſe that followed him; ſince they are inſtructed in it, the ſame way the Apoſtles themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and commanded, by ſubmitting to, and obeying thoſe that are over them: Why do you ſay they are deprived of the Word of God?</hi> I anſwer. For theſe Reaſons:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe that which they have of the Word of God is but very little, in compariſon of what they are deprived of.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe much of that little, if taken with thoſe gloſſes, and underſtood in that ſenſe which they put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, is not the Word of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe much of that little, which in popular Diſcourſe is delivered to them as the Word of God, is nothing leſs. This the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> muſt be forc'd to grant, unleſs he can prove theſe two things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That both parts of a Contradiction may be true: For nothing is more obvious, than that thoſe Propoſitions are, by many of the Roman Clergy, delivered as the Word of God, which are contradictory the one to the other. For Example: One ſays, the <hi>Wood</hi> of the <hi>Croſs</hi> is to be adored; another, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt only</hi> is to be adored in the preſence of the Croſs. That the <hi>Pope</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:49460:40"/> has Power to <hi>depoſe Kings,</hi> one makes it Hereſy to deny, another to affirm it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That that may be the Word of God, which is plainly contrary to what God hath taught in the holy Scriptures; for ſo are many things taught by many of their Paſtors: For example; <hi>That the ſacred Body of the Mother of Jeſus is endow'd with a ſuper-ſeraphical activity, whereby ſhe can render her ſelf preſent in a moment to all her Devotees; vieweth all their Actions, Words and Concerns, and can aid them at whatever diſtance at all times, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Calamities be</hi> &amp;c. <note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Life and Glory of the Holy Mary.</hi> p. 69.</note>. When the Repreſenter ſhall have proved theſe two Propoſitions: That Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions may be true, and that that may be the Word of God, that is plainly contrary to the Word of God, we may then perhaps be perſwaded to believe, that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Prieſts ſpeak nothing but <hi>Oracles.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>That which is mentioned as the next <hi>Miſconſtruction,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Inference II.</note> or <hi>falſe Inference</hi> of the Proteſtants, is this: <hi>That the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt takes up all his Belief upon truſt, he is led through all the Myſteries of his Religion by the hand, without ſeeing which way or whither he goes. All from beginning to end is Blindneſs and Ignorance,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="q" place="margin">Chap. 7. p. 49.</note>. And what ſays the Repreſenter in anſwer to this? <hi>A Papiſt believes as the Church of God</hi> (that is the preſent Church of <hi>Rome) teaches.</hi> And does not he take all his Belief upon truſt, who without examination, believes whatſoever his Church teaches? But how does he know what his Church teaches? his Prieſt tells him. Well, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves as the <hi>Church teaches,</hi> he believes the Church tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches this or that, becauſe his Prieſt tells him ſo; does he not then take his Church's Faith, and his own too, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49460:41"/> truſt from his Prieſt? No: For he does not believe <hi>blindly, but knowingly and underſtandingly, ſo far as the littleneſs of humane Reaſon, and his own Capacity will give him leave.</hi> How does this appear? Becauſe <hi>in order to this, his Church has provided him of variety of</hi> Learned <hi>Books, explicating to him the ſenſe of the Scriptures, as likewiſe the Articles of his Creed, every Myſtery of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the ten Commandments, the Sacraments, and the whole Duty of a Chriſtian, and this in ſuch numbers, both in</hi> Latin <hi>and</hi> Engliſh, <hi>and other Languages,</hi> &amp;c. What? <hi>Learned</hi> Books for the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned?</hi> and in <hi>Latin</hi> too, for thoſe who underſtand not a word of Latin? May they not learn as much from the Latin Bible, as from a Latin Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication? Well may they believe <hi>underſtandingly,</hi> when their Church has provided them of ſuch Books for that purpoſe, which are above their <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe, he has Books in <hi>Engliſh, and other Languages.</hi> In <hi>England</hi> he is better provided of Books, than in other Countries; But does he not take all theſe upon truſt too, ſince he is not ſuffered to examine ſo much as one of them by the Scripture? Yea, is not his Belief of theſe Books, a plain Argument, that he believes <hi>blindfold?</hi> Becauſe many ſuch things are contain'd in them, which if he impartially examined, he could never yield his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to. That I may not be thought to ſpeak at random, I ſhall give a ſingle Inſtance (out of that great number I could produce) in each of the Heads before-mentioned. 1. For the <hi>ſenſe of Scripture;</hi> he muſt take it upon truſt, who takes that Dominion aſcribed to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> to be meant in theſe Texts quoted for it, <hi>viz.</hi> that God hath given her ſovereign Dominion in Heaven over the Angels <hi>(the Queen ſtood at thy right Hand, Pſalm.</hi> 44.) on Earth over Men <hi>(Kings reign by me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.) and over Hell and the Devil; <hi>(ſhe ſhall bruiſe thy</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49460:41"/> 
                     <hi>Head Gen.</hi> 3.) <note n="r" place="margin">Jeſus, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Joſeph. p. 167, 168.</note> 2. For the <hi>Articles of his Creed:</hi> He believes upon truſt, who believes Contradictions; and ſo does he, who believes, that by the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in the <hi>Creed,</hi> is meant the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick. 3. For the <hi>Myſteries of his Religion,</hi> I appeal to all Men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he does not take them upon truſt, who takes them, as they are delivered in a Book lately printed <note n="s" place="margin">Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations on the Life and Glory of the Holy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note>; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly this of the Nativity of the Mother of <hi>Jeſus:</hi>
                     <q>That <hi>Holy Mary,</hi> being by a ſingular Priviledg, (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of her Divine Maternity) perfectly innocent, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and full of Grace, Wiſdom, and all Virtues, in the <hi>firſt poſitive inſtant,</hi> of the Infuſion of her Soul, ſhe from thence forth ever exerciſed the ſublime Operations of the <hi>Contemplative</hi> and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitive</hi> Life, without recourſe to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Imagination, or dependence on ſenſe, by the help of <hi>abſtractive Lights,</hi> divinely infus'd, repreſenting, 1. The ſeveral <hi>Eſſences, Attributes</hi> and <hi>Motions</hi> of the whole Body of the Creation, in their ſeveral degrees and ſtations. 2. The <hi>Divinity</hi> of God, with its manifold <hi>Emanations, Operations, and</hi> unexplicable <hi>Comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> 3. And the <hi>Humanity</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> with all the <hi>Orders</hi> of Grace, <hi>Myſteries</hi> of Salvation, and <hi>extatick Loves</hi> of the Saints, whereby her great Soul was ſo compleatly actuated, even in the <hi>Womb</hi> of her Mother, that her <hi>Contemplations, Sallies</hi> of Love, and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions</hi> with God were reſtleſs, ever increaſing in their vigor, and ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiating through the vaſt Motions and Methods of <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Love.</hi> Thus Divine <hi>Mary</hi> became ſtill more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, repleniſh'd with Grace, and <hi>abſorpt</hi> in the Abyſs of ſupernatural Perfection; which wonderfully encreaſed the <hi>languiſhings</hi> of Angels, Souls in <hi>Limbo,</hi> and of her holy Parents for the hour of her <hi>Birth</hi> 
                        <note n="t" place="margin">Ibid. p. 44, 45.</note>.</q> This is a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> (and ſo are ſeveral others in the ſame Book) which, I fear, the <hi>Vulgar</hi> are not able to believe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49460:42"/> 
                     <hi>knowingly.</hi> 4. For the <hi>ten Commandments,</hi> he muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>blindly,</hi> who believes he has them intire in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, when ſo conſiderable a part is left out; <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image, nor the Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of any thing that is in Heaven above,</hi> &amp;c. Or that he hath the fourth Commandment ſincerely delivered in theſe words; <hi>Remember to ſanctify the holy Days.</hi> We are told I know, in the <hi>Abridgment of Chriſtian Doctrine,</hi> that the Church cannot be <hi>accuſed of the leaſt ſhadow</hi> of omitting any parts of the Commandments <note n="u" place="margin">P. 113.</note>. But how can that be, when it is before acknowledged, that a great Part of the Text is omitted? <hi>Becauſe in no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Bible, is there one Syllable left out.</hi> But what is this to the Vulgar, who are not permitted to read any Catholick Bible? who know no more of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than what they find in their Catechiſm. 5. As to the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> Had he not need truſt ſtrongly, who believes, that Chriſt inſtituted the Sacrament of Order, in ſaying, <hi>Do this</hi> 
                     <note n="w" place="margin">Rhemes Teſt. Annot. in Luke 22. <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>Abridgment of Chriſt. Doct.</hi> p. 184, 185.</note>? Behold here the Lights the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Papiſt enjoys! Is it not now as manifeſt as Light it ſelf, <hi>That whoſoever reproaches him with Blindneſs in the midst of ſo many Lights, may with as good Reaſon prove him to be in the dark, when Noon-day ſhines upon him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Eſpecially conſidering, <hi>That beſides theſe Books, the Church hath given direction to all Pariſh-Prieſts, to expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate on Sundays and Holy-days, the Goſpel, and ſome My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Faith, to ſuch as are under their Charge,</hi> &amp;c. But have we not reaſon to believe, that the Explications of their Pariſh Prieſts are anſwerable to thoſe we meet with in their Books? and then notwithſtanding theſe <hi>Helps</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtances,</hi> not only ſome, but many of his Church, may <hi>believe without underſtanding;</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>condemned of Negligence and Sloth,</hi> in the uſe of thoſe means their Church has provided for them. And
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49460:42"/> if the Pariſh-Prieſts are generally as ignorant, as many Learned Men of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> tell us they are, even they themſelves believe <hi>without underſtanding,</hi> and therefore much more the People.</p>
                  <p>But by what follows, the Vulgar Papiſts are very blame-worthy, if they know not the Scripture better, than the Vulgar of any other Communion. <hi>For it is an unqueſtionable Truth, that when a Book contains high My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Religion, Myſteries ſuperior to all Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and thoſe not deliver'd in expreſſions ſuited to every Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, but obnoxious to various interpretations, that the People is in all probability likely to have more of the true ſenſe of this Book, and to be better informed of the Truth of the Myſteries it contains, who are inſtructed in it by the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of that Communion, and taught it by their Paſtors, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, and thoſe whom God hath placed over them, to govern and feed the Flock; than any other People, who have the Book put into their own hands, to read it, and ſearch it, and ſatisfie themſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In anſwer to which I ſhall propoſe a few Queſtions to the Repreſenter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>1ſt.</hi> Whether it be an unqueſtionable Truth, that when a Book contains not <hi>only</hi> high Myſteries, but ſuch things as for the far greater part, are not above the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of the Vulgar; that he ſhall have more of the true ſenſe of this Book, who is inſtructed in it by his Paſtors <hi>only,</hi> than he who is inſtructed in it by them, and ſtudies it himſelf too? In all Sciences there are ſome Myſteries; now is he likely to underſtand any other Science better, who takes only the Inſtructions of his Teachers, than he, who together with them, diligently ſtudies it himſelf alſo?</p>
                  <p>2. Suppoſe nothing but high Myſteries were contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Book; yet may not he as well underſtand theſe Myſteries, who is inſtructed in them by the Learned,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49460:43"/> and ſearches them himſelf, as he that truſts only to the Inſtructions of the Learned?</p>
                  <p>3. Is it for the ſake of theſe high Myſteries, that the reading of this Book is forbidden the Vulgar? If ſo, then, 1. Why was it not forbidden ſooner? ſince theſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries were in it from the Beginning. 2. Why are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Books publiſh'd for their uſe, in which are Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſuperior to all <hi>Senſe and Reaſon, and thoſe not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd in expreſſions ſuited to every Capacity, but ſuch as may be wreſted by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtable to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction?</hi> Such I mean, as the <hi>Contemplations of the Life and Glory,</hi> &amp;c. Jeſus, Maria, Joſeph, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore,</p>
                  <p>4. Is it not evident that it is not for the ſake of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, but of thoſe things which are too plain and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to vulgar underſtandings, that the reading of this Book is prohibited?</p>
                  <p>But he confirms what he ſays, both by Reaſon and Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By Reaſon. <hi>Are not the Paſtors more capable of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the People, than the People are of teaching themſelves?</hi> An admirable Reaſon! Let us ſee how it will hold in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters. Is not the Maſter or Tutor more capable of teaching the Scholar, than the Scholar is of teaching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? He therefore will have more of the true ſenſe of any Book in Logick, Phyſicks or Metaphyſicks, that never looks into the Book himſelf, but only hears a Lecture once in a Week or Month from his Tutor, upon ſome part of it, than he that makes the Book his conſtant ſtudy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As admirable are the Proofs from Scripture. <hi>We know</hi> Moſes <hi>gave the Book of the Law to the</hi> Levites <hi>to keep and read it every ſeven years to the People: And in King</hi> Jehoſaphat<hi>'s Reign the Prieſts and Levites did read it, and teach the People; ſo did</hi> Jeremy <hi>by God's Command, ſo</hi> Iſaiah, <hi>ſo</hi> Ezekicl.<hi>—And did not our Bleſſed Saviour</hi>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:49460:43"/> 
                     <hi>take the Book of the Prophet, and read it, and expound it to the People? And was not this the Office of the Apoſtles and Deacons?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The Argument is this. The Prieſts and Levites read the Book of the Law, and taught the People; ſo did <hi>Jeremy, Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel;</hi> Yea our Saviour and his Apoſtles read and expounded the Scripture to the People: Therefore they will underſtand more of the true ſenſe of the Scripture, who never read it, than thoſe who do. What pity was it, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, and our Saviour and his Apoſtles, did not underſtand the force of this Argument? for if they had, they would, no doubt, have forbidden the People to read the Scripture, and then we had never been peſter'd with thoſe Sects and Hereſies that ſpring from it: But they were altogether unacquainted with the <hi>Roman</hi> Politicks. Tho therefore they read the Scripture to the People themſelves, and read it in the <hi>vulgar Tongue;</hi> yet they left it free to the People to read it, and not only ſo, but laid it as a Duty upon them.</p>
                  <p>He adds: <hi>For this intention was Ananias ſent to Saul, Peter to Cornelius, and Philip to the Eunuch, who profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly own'd, he could not underſtand the Prophet in ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a Point as that of the Meſſias, without an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">P. 51.</note>: None of which Inſtances make any thing for him, but that of the Eunuch makes much againſt him. For the Eunuch was reading the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> tho he could not underſtand him; and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> 
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Hom. 35. in Geneſ.</note> and others <note n="z" place="margin">Non intelligebat Scripturae ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum homo prophanus &amp; idiota; &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quoniam pio ſtudio legebat, ſubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mittitur illi Philippus interpres, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur Eunuchus in virum, tingitur aquâ, &amp; ater Aethiops niveo agni immaculati vellere induitur; ſubito<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ex mancipio prophanae Reginae, fit ſervus Ieſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. Eraſ. Epiſt. <hi>l.</hi> 29. Epiſt. 82.</note> obſerve, that God as a Reward of his Diligence and Piety, in doing what he was able, ſent him a Teacher. And what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows hence? Firſt, that they ought
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49460:44"/> not to forbear the reading of the Scriptures, who do not underſtand them. Secondly, That they who thus read them with a pious Mind, ſhall be graciouſly accepted and rewarded by God. Theſe Inferences are not mine, but both of them St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s.</p>
                  <p>It follows; <hi>Since therefore the Papiſts, in delivering the Scriptures, come neareſt to this method, commanded by God in the Old Law, preſcribed and practiſed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the New,</hi> &amp;c. If he mean, that this was the <hi>only</hi> Method commanded by God in the Old Law, and preſcribed by Chriſt in the New, I have already ſhew'd it to be falſe. If he mean that this was <hi>one</hi> Method, then how widely remote the Concluſion is from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, will appear only by ſetting them together. One Method commanded by God in the Old Law, was, that the Prieſts and Levites ſhould read the Law, and explain it to the People: the like Method was preſcribed and practiſed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the New Law: Therefore the Papiſts, in withholding the Scripture from the Common People, come neareſt to the Method commanded by God in the Old Law, and preſcribed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the New. Where lies the Connection? And yet I confeſs it follows as clearly as this, That the Scriptures were not in the Vulgar Tongue, becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to <hi>Timothy, Thou haſt learned the Holy Scriptures from a Child</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ledeſma de Script. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinis quavis lingua non le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendis. c. 5.</note>. I ſhould have thought the quite contrary had followed, had I not been taught otherwiſe, by one that follows the guidance of the Infallible Church. Had the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſpoken the whole Truth in the Premiſſes, the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had been unavoidable for the Proteſtants, who in delivering the Scripture to the People, obſerve the ſame Method that God appointed under the Law, and Chriſt and his Apoſtles under the Goſpel. What follows upon this Head, we have had before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:49460:44"/>
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>That which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> reckons as another <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruction</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Inference</hi> 3.</note> of the Proteſtants, is this; <hi>That the Reaſon why the Vulgar Papiſts are not permitted to read the Bible, is for fear leſt they ſhould diſcover the Errors of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> 
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">Chap. 8. p. 53.</note>. 'Tis true, the Proteſtants aſſign this for one Reaſon; but when he brings in the Proteſtant ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I can apprehend no other,</hi> he miſrepreſents them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they aſſign others, tho they take this to be the chief. Now this, he ſays, is a <hi>Miſconſtruction that lies ſo open, that there needs no more than a glimpſe of Reaſon to diſcover it.</hi> Let us therefore ſee, whether there be ſo much as a glimpſe in thoſe pretended Reaſons he brings to confute it; which are theſe two.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That tho the Vulgar and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned of the Papiſts, have not in ſome Countries the Bible promiſcuouſly allow'd amongst them; yet that in thoſe ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and all others, there's no College, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, Community, or place of Learning, but where the Scriptures are publickly read and expounded</hi> 
                     <note n="(h)" place="margin">Ibid.</note>.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That there can be no ground for this Pretenſion, at leaſt here in</hi> England, <hi>where the Bible in Engliſh, or the Rhemes Teſtament, is to be found in moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Families</hi> 
                     <note n="(i)" place="margin">P. 54.</note>.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>That in all Popiſh Countries, there's no College, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, Community, or place of Learning, but where the Scripture is publickly read and expounded.</hi> Now <hi>if they (viz.</hi> the Proteſtants) <hi>ſhould conſider this, is it poſſible</hi> (ſays the Repreſenter) <hi>for them to believe, that that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint is upon the Vulgar, for fear they ſhould ſee into the Follies of their Religion?</hi> It is poſſible: and becauſe we ſee a Papiſt can believe contrary to Senſe and Reaſon, I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49460:45"/> add, that it is not only poſſible, but there is great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Proteſtants to believe this. And that,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe even Papiſts themſelves believe it. So did the Biſhops that met at <hi>Bononia,</hi> to conſult about the eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: For having given it as their laſt and weightieſt Advice, to <hi>Julius</hi> III, <hi>That he labour to the uttermoſt, that as little as may be of the Goſpel, eſpecially in the Vulgar Tongue, be read in the Cities that were under his Dominions, and that that little might ſuffice which is wont to be read in the Maſs.</hi> They add, <hi>This in ſhort is the Book which, beſides others, hath raiſed thoſe Tempeſts and Whirlwinds which we are almoſt carried away with: And the truth is, if any Man ſhall diligently conſider this Book, and then view in order one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the things which are wont to be done in our Churches, he will ſee that there is a very great difference between them, and that this our Doctrine is altogether diverſe from that, and oft-times even contrary to it; which as ſoon as Men underſtand, being ſtirred up by ſome Learned Men of our Adverſaries, they never give over clamouring againſt us, till they have render'd us odious to all Men</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Hic ille eſt liber, qui praeter caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros haſce no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis tempeſtates ac turbines concitavit, quibus prope abrepti ſumus. Et ſane ſi quis illum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligenter expendar, deinde quae in noſtris fieri Eccleſiiis conſueverunt, ſingula ordine contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platur; videbit plurimum inter ſe diſſidere, &amp; hanc doctrinam noſtram ab illa prorſus diverſam eſſe, ac ſaepe contrariam etiam: Quod ſimul atque homines intelligunt, à docto ſcilicet aliquo Adverſariorum noſtrorum ſtimulati, non ante clamandi in nos finem faciunt, donec re tandem pervulgata nos inviſos omnibus reddiderint. Conſil. de Rom. Eccleſ. Stab.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Of the ſame Belief was <hi>Peter Sutor,</hi> as appears by theſe words; <hi>Since many things are deliver'd to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, which are not expreſly in the Holy Scriptures; will not the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned, obſerving theſe things, be ready to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, complaining that ſo great Burdens are laid upon them, by which their Goſpel-Liberty is ſorely abridged? And will they not be eaſily withdrawn from obſerving the</hi>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49460:45"/> 
                     <hi>Conſtitutions of the Church, when they ſhall ſee that they are not contain'd in the Law of Chriſt</hi> 
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Sed cum multa palam tradantur ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervanda, quae Sacris in literis expreſſe non habentur; nonne Idiotae haec animadvertentes facile murmura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, conquerentes cur tantae ſibi imponantur Sarcinae, quibus &amp; libertas Evangelica ita gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicer elevatur? Nonne &amp; facile retrahentur ab obſervantia Inſtitutionum Eccleſiaſticarum, quando eas in lege Chriſti animadverterint non contineri. De Tranſlat. Bibl. c. 22. Fo. 96.</note>.</p>
                  <p>To which may be added all thoſe (which make a vaſt number) who (as the Cardinal <hi>Rodolpho Pio di Carpi)</hi> believe, that if the Bible be in the Vulgar Tongue, all Men will become Hereticks <note n="m" place="margin">Soave<hi>'s Hiſt. of the Counc. of</hi> Trent. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 460.</note>. For who do they uſually mean by Hereticks, but thoſe who by reading the Bible, do firſt diſcover, and then renounce their Errors? Now tho, I confeſs, there are ſome things believed by Papiſts, which I think it impoſſible for a Proteſtant to believe; yet I doubt not but the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> will grant, that the belief of this, is as eaſy to a Proteſtant as it is to a Papiſt: And that ſince it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by Papiſts, there is very good reaſon why Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſhould believe it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Since they allow the Vulgar the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their own Tongue, what probable Reaſon can be given why they leave out this part, <hi>Thou ſhalt not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Tho to ſtop their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Mouths, they now put theſe words into the Engliſh Catechiſms.</note> 
                     <hi>make to thy ſelf any graven Image,</hi> &amp;c. but this; that they dare not let their Laity compare their Doctrine and their Practice, with this Scripture? It is, I know, commonly ſaid, that this is done in compliance with the weak Memories of the People: But he muſt be of a <hi>weak</hi> underſtanding, who is ſatisfied with this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; eſpecially conſidering, how tedious ſome of their Offices of Devotion are, which are compoſed for the uſe of the Laity.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is no Thanks to them that the Bible is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to the Learned, becauſe it is impoſſible it ſhould
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49460:46"/> be kept from them, as long as it is ſuffer'd in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. But it is plain they are afraid of them, in that they do not allow them, however <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>pious;</hi> but at the Biſhop's diſcretion, to read any Verſions of the Old Teſtament; Nor do they give the Biſhop leave to permit any Man, how learned ſoever, to read any Verſions of the New, made by thoſe who are cenſured by their Church, but confine them to the Vulgar Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note n="n" place="margin">Reg. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Trid.</note>. And to make as ſure of them as they can, they tie them up as cloſe as they are able, from giving any ſuch Interpretation of it, as may be prejudicial to their new Faith. And yet not truſting to this Security, they endeavour, as much as may be, to conceal from them thoſe Scriptures which are repugnant to their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Which is,</p>
                  <p>4. A plain Argument, That it is the Bible it ſelf they take to be miſchievous to them. Why elſe, 1. Did they blot thoſe words out of the Margin and Index of <hi>Rob. Stephen</hi>'s Bible, which were the ſame with thoſe in the Text? For Example; <hi>Abraham was juſtified by Faith. He that believeth in Chriſt, ſhall not die for ever.</hi> They that blotted theſe out of the Index, that the Reader might not thereby be directed to find them, would they not (if they durſt) have blotted them out of the Text too? 2. Why elſe have they purged, not only out of the Ancient Fathers, but many late Learned Writers of their own Church, many Paſſages of the Scripture it ſelf? 3. Why was it commended as a moſt meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Act in <hi>John Della Cava</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Benevento,</hi> That <hi>tho he had not openly and expreſly condemn'd the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, yet obſcurely and covertly he had? becauſe in his large Catalogue of Hereticks, he had reprobated a great part of that Doctrine, which is contain'd in the Goſpel; eſpecially ſome certain Heads which were moſt oppoſite to the Church of</hi> Rome
<note n="p" place="margin">Conſil. de Rom. Eccleſ. Stab.</note>.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49460:46"/>
                  <p> The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> proceeds; <hi>If their Religion be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Scripture as you pretend, is it not more likely the Learned ſhould make this diſcovery in their reading the Bible, than the Vulgar if they had the like liberty?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>To which I return theſe two Things;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If the Learned are as free from Prejudice, Pride, Vain-glory, Covetouſneſs, and other evil Affections, which darken Mens Minds, it is more likely they ſhould make this Diſcovery than the Vulgar; if not, the Vulgar are better qualified to make it than they: For tho Learning, when joyn'd with a ſincere love of Truth, is a great advantage for the diſcovery of it; yet when deſtitute of this, it is as great a hinderance. The Learned among the Jews, in the days of our Saviour, are a demonſtrative Proof of this. Tho <hi>Moſes</hi> and all the Prophets bore Teſtimony to him, yet the Scribes and Phariſees were not able to ſee it: Why? becauſe they were prepoſſeſſed with the Prejudices of a Pompous Meſſias, they ſought Glory of Men, they had carnal Affections, and a worldly Intereſt to ſerve; tho there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Characters of the Meſſias were viſible in him, yet becauſe he was not a Meſſias for their turn, they could not diſcern them; I ſay, not only, they <hi>did</hi> not, but without firſt laying aſide their corrupt Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they <hi>could</hi> not: And ſo our Saviour himſelf ſays; <hi>Ye cannot hear my Word</hi> 
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Joh. 8. 43.</note>. And <hi>how can ye believe which receive Honour one of another</hi> 
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Joh. 5. 44.</note>? How <hi>wife and prudent</hi> ſoever they were in other Matters, they were not capable of the Truths of the Goſpel; and therefore they were hid from them, while they were revealed to Babes <note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 11. 25.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Now how few in compariſon of the Learned in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have not ſome carnal Intereſt to ſerve? How few are not prepoſſeſs'd with ſome ſuch falſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49460:47"/> Principle, that be the Scripture never ſo clear againſt them, will ſo blind their eyes, that they ſhall not be able to diſcern it? Should the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teach Murder and Adultery to be Vertues, he who makes it a Fundamental Article of his Faith, that ſhe cannot err, would not be able to ſee that they are Sins; but would find out ſome other ſenſe of theſe Commandments than the words plainly import.</p>
                  <p>In ſhort; this Argument the Learned Jews made uſe of againſt our Bleſſed Saviour; <hi>Have any of the Phariſees believed on him? But this People who know not the Law, are curs'd</hi> 
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Joh. 7. 48, 49.</note>. As much as to ſay; Were he the true Meſſias, the Learned Phariſees who ſtudy the Law, would certainly know it; ſince therefore they do not believe on him, no heed is to be given to the ignorant Multitude. Were therefore this Argument of force, it would have juſtified the Vulgar Jews in reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt. But,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Many of their Learned Men have made this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. How many ſuch were the chief Inſtruments of the Reformation, and they doubtleſs diſcover'd the Errors of their Church, before they forſook it. How many continually ſince have forſaken their Communion, in ſpite of all worldly Motives to the contrary? How many who have not left their Communion, have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven abundant Teſtimony by their Writings, that they were convinced of their Errors, ſome in one thing, ſome in another. Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Contare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> will be owned for as Learned Men as moſt of their Time; and they diſcover'd the Error of Prayer and Service in an Unknown Tongue. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in the laſt Age, and <hi>Arnaud</hi> and his Brethren the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> in this, have expoſed to all the World the Error I now write againſt. The Learned Men of the Church of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49460:47"/> 
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> who have rejected the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Books from the Canon of Scripture, are too many to be particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned; for that they are no part of the Canon, was Catholic Doctrine at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf (as a Learned Biſhop of our own Church has prov'd) but ten Years before the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> And whoſoever has read the Hiſtory of that Council, cannot but ſee, that the denial of the Cup to the Laity, was diſcovered to be an Error, by many Learned Men of that Church. Yea, the great Article of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> many of their moſt Learned Men, both in the preſent and in foregoing Ages, could never perſwade themſelves to believe. How many more of their Errors, have been diſcover'd and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to the World by, <hi>Caſſander, Wicelius, Eraſmus, Picus Mirandula,</hi> and many other Learned Men, who died in Communion with them, I ſhall not ſtay to mention: But ſhall only make this Inference, that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> would never have argued at this rate, had he not vainly thought, that the Proteſtants are as little acquainted with the Writings of the Papiſts, as the Papiſts generally are with thoſe of the Proteſtants.</p>
                  <p>What follows concerning <hi>Mechanicks</hi> and <hi>Apron-ſtrings,</hi> the <hi>Anvil,</hi> the <hi>Needle</hi> and the <hi>Ell,</hi> I ſuppoſe he did not intend for Arguments, but only for Ornaments and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhments, and therefore I paſs them over.</p>
                  <p>He adds; <hi>Is it probable, that every Man amongst the Papiſts, no ſooner becomes Scholar, but he turns Atheiſt?</hi> No. <hi>That upon their ſearch in the Bible; they plainly ſee</hi> all <hi>the Errours of their Religion, and yet are ſo bewitched as to go on boldly and jocondly to the Devil, without ſpeaking a word, or moving a ſtep to ſave their own Souls, or their Relations</hi> 
                     <note n="u" place="margin">P. 53, 54.</note>. I will not ſay, that <hi>every</hi> Learned Papiſt ſees <hi>[all]</hi> the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of their Religion: It may ſuffice, that <hi>many</hi> of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49460:48"/> them have diſcover'd many of their Errors, &amp; have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten boldly againſt them. And for thoſe who diſcover their Errors, and yet profeſs to believe them, it is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary they ſhould be <hi>Atheiſts:</hi> I hope thoſe Gentlemen are no <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> who for ſeveral years late paſt, have <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>profeſs'd</hi> with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> their Religion approves Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and mental Reſervation: Tho I confeſs that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Argument is ſo great a Bar to my turning Papiſt, that I cannot at preſent imagine, that I can ever be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to that Religion, which allows ſuch groſs Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. I hope by this time the Repreſenter ſees, how <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>ill-grounded</hi> his own Arguments are.</p>
                  <p>2. But he asks; <hi>What ground can there be for this Pretenſion, at leaſt here in</hi> England, <hi>where the Bible in Engliſh, or the Rhemes Teſtament is to be found in moſt Catholic Families?</hi> If it be ſo, who is to be thanked for it? Not their Church-men: For tho they are more indulgent to their People here in <hi>England,</hi> yet it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they dare not be otherwiſe, ſince ſhould they hold them to as ſtrict terms here, as they do where they are in full poſſeſſion, it might endanger their loſing them. Beſides, that it is impoſſible to keep the Bible here; from thoſe who have a mind to read it; for if they have it not with their leave, they can have it without it. But yet, to keep them as much as may be from it, they endeavour to perſwade them, that it is a ſin to read it without leave; and many are ſo poſſeſſed with this Belief, that they acknowledg they dare not read it, nor any other Book offer'd to them by Proteſtants, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leave firſt obtain'd from their Ghoſtly Father: and were <hi>England</hi> as much in their Power as <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> are, a Bible in the Vulgar Tongue would be as rarely found in any Family here, as it is in thoſe Nations;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49460:48"/> tho I ſee no reaſon, but they may freely allow them the Rhemes Teſtament, becauſe they have ſo transform'd it into their own likeneſs, that one would think, they need fear no danger from it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the prohibition of the Bible be, as you pretend in other Countries, for fear of the Vulgar diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Errors of their Religion; how comes it, that they don't make this Diſcovery here?</hi> Some may not make this Diſcovery, becauſe of thoſe invincible Prejudices they are prepoſſeſs'd with: Others may not make it, becauſe they do not ſee with their own Eyes, but leave it to their Prieſts to ſee for them: Yet 'tis ſtrange the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſhould ask, <hi>How comes it they do not make this Diſcovery?</hi> as if none had made it; when, to the great grief of their Church, ſuch vaſt numbers have long ſince made it. Does he not know, That one Objection againſt tranſlating the Bible in in King <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII days, was, That if Lay-men had the Bible in their Mother Tongue, it would make them all Hereticks? Does he not know, how far the Event has anſwered the Prediction? that whereas before the whole Nation was generally of their Belief, ſo many have forſaken them ſince, that now perhaps one or two in an hundred, are as many as they can challenge?</p>
                  <p>He ſays, <hi>Many have quitted that Communion upon other Motives, beſt known to themſelves, but never any one could I meet with left them yet, by reading and following the Word of God.</hi> He has it ſeems, met with few who have left them; nor could it be expected he ſhould meet with many; for ſo many had left them before his time, that few in compariſon remain'd to leave them now. And thoſe who left their Communion in K. <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII days, could not leave it upon worldly Motives, becauſe, after he gave leave to print the Bible in Engliſh, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49460:49"/> encouragement to all Men to read it, he not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a Member of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelf, but a zealous Perſecutor of thoſe who forſook it. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he <hi>meets with none who deſert them now:</hi> If he does not, yet many others do; and I preſume, thoſe that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them now, their only Motive muſt be, <hi>to follow the Word of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>if the reading the Scriptures is ſuch a defeat to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery as you give out; is it likely thoſe who have been bred up to the reading of the Bible, and have made it their Study and Companion, ſhould ever embrace that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion?</hi> Not more unlikely, than that thoſe who have been bred up to the reading of the Bible, ſhould imbrace divers other Opinions and Practices, that are utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with it; which we frequently ſee ſome Men do. Tho, I queſtion not, but if he examine their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, he will find but few of them ſuch as have made the Bible their <hi>Study and Companion.</hi> And for thoſe who have been bred up to the reading it, but never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd themſelves to conſider it, it is not more unlikely, that they ſhould imbrace Popery, tho never ſo plainly contrary to it, than that thoſe ſhould, who never ſo much as ſaw it. I ſhall not paſs a Cenſure upon their late Proſelytes; but I am perſwaded the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> himſelf will confeſs, that ſome of them are ſuch as they have no reaſon to boaſt of.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. Marg. for <hi>Mandeuent,</hi> read <hi>Mandement.</hi> P. 8. Marg. for <hi>Proſanes,</hi> r. <hi>Profanes.</hi> P. 11. l. 6. after <hi>that,</hi> add <hi>it.</hi> l. laſt, for <hi>Acaia,</hi> r. <hi>Achaia.</hi> P. 16. Marg. l. 4. for <hi>it,</hi> r. <hi>et.</hi> P 19. Marg. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. l. 2, and 3, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. P. 30. after <hi>reading,</hi> add <hi>it.</hi> P. 53. l. 27. for <hi>goſly,</hi> r. <hi>groſly.</hi> P. 69. l. 7. for <hi>reci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> r. <hi>reci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> P. 80. Marg. r. <hi>contempletur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49460:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
